<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The warnings of the Lord to the men of this generation particularly, to those in power, who are lately past away, ere they so passed; and to them that remain, who are* ready to passe except they speedily repent. As they were given forth in sundry letters, and sent to Oliver Cromwel, Richard his son, late Protectors. The Parrliament [sic] succeeding. The council of officers of the Army. The Council of State. A Member of the Parliament and Council of State, and Committee of Safety. The general council of the officers of the Army a citizen of London, and one of the commissioners of the militia there. By his servant George Bishop. Who is moved of the Lord (now) to publish them, ... Whereunto is added, The burden of Dumah upon occasion of this query, sent in a letter by one related to the Army, viz. - Watchman! What of the night? Watchman! What of the night?</title>
            <author>Bishop, George, d. 1668.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28252</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3016</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210716</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825443</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825443</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29825</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28252)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29825)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2165:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The warnings of the Lord to the men of this generation particularly, to those in power, who are lately past away, ere they so passed; and to them that remain, who are* ready to passe except they speedily repent. As they were given forth in sundry letters, and sent to Oliver Cromwel, Richard his son, late Protectors. The Parrliament [sic] succeeding. The council of officers of the Army. The Council of State. A Member of the Parliament and Council of State, and Committee of Safety. The general council of the officers of the Army a citizen of London, and one of the commissioners of the militia there. By his servant George Bishop. Who is moved of the Lord (now) to publish them, ... Whereunto is added, The burden of Dumah upon occasion of this query, sent in a letter by one related to the Army, viz. - Watchman! What of the night? Watchman! What of the night?</title>
                  <author>Bishop, George, d. 1668.</author>
                  <author>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658, recipient.</author>
                  <author>Cromwell, Richard, 1626-1712, recipient.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by M. Inman, and are to be sold at the Three Bibles in Pauls Church-yard, and by Richard Moon, bookseller in Windstreet in Bristol,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The asterisk in title refers to printed marginal note: 17th. of the 10th. mon. 1659. The words "Oliver Cromwell, .. his son," are joined by a right brace with the words "late Protectors." to right; the words "Oliver Cromwel, .. militia there." are joined by a left bracket.</note>
                  <note>Copy stained with heavy print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29825:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> Warnings <hi>of the LORD To the</hi> Men <hi>of</hi> this <hi>GENERATION</hi> PARTICULARLY, <hi>To</hi> thoſe <hi>in</hi> Power, <hi>who are</hi> lately paſt <hi>away, ere</hi> they <hi>ſo</hi> paſſed; <hi>and to</hi> Them <hi>that Remain, who are</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">17th. of the 10th. Mon. 1659</note> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to paſſe <hi>except</hi> They ſpeedily Repent.</p>
            <p>AS They <hi>were given forth in</hi> ſundry <hi>Letters, and ſent TO</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>OLIVER CROMWEL,</item>
                        <item>RICHARD <hi>his Son,</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list> Late <hi>Protectors.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> PARRLIAMENT <hi>ſucceeding.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> Council of Officers <hi>of the</hi> ARMY.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> COUNCIL <hi>of</hi> STATE.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Member <hi>of the</hi> Parliament <hi>and</hi> Council <hi>of</hi> State, <hi>and</hi> Committee <hi>of</hi> Safety.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> General Council <hi>of the</hi> Officers <hi>of the</hi> Army</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Citizen <hi>of</hi> London <hi>and</hi> One <hi>of the</hi> Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners <hi>of the</hi> Militia <hi>there.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> His <hi>Servant</hi> GEORGE BISHOP.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who is</hi> moved, <hi>of the</hi> Lord (now) <hi>to</hi> Publiſh them, <hi>to the end, That</hi> all <hi>may ſee that</hi> He <hi>hath given to</hi> every <hi>ſort of</hi> theſe <hi>men, a</hi> Day, <hi>who gives to</hi> Nations, Kingdoms, States, <hi>a</hi> Day <hi>wherein</hi> to know, and to do the Things that appertain unto their Peace, <hi>which</hi> they <hi>not heeding, and the</hi> hour <hi>of</hi> their Viſitation paſſing Over, they <hi>fall</hi> irrecoverably, and are left without excuſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ALSO, As a</hi> Testimony <hi>to the</hi> Approaching, Great, <hi>and</hi> Terrible <hi>Day of the</hi> Lord, <hi>wherein</hi> he will Reward every Man according to his Works.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereunto is added, The</hi> Burden <hi>of</hi> Dumah <hi>upon occaſion of</hi> this <hi>Query, ſent in a</hi> LETTER <hi>by</hi> One <hi>related to the</hi> ARMY, Viz.</p>
            <p>—Watchman! What of the Night? Watchman! What of the Night?</p>
            <p>O Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem! thou that killeſt the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them that are ſent unto Thee, how often would I have gathered thee as a Hen gathereth her Chicken under her wings, but ye would not? Behold, your houſe is left unto you deſolate; for verily I ſay unto you, Ye ſhall not henceforth ſee my face, till ye ſhall ſay, Bleſsed is he that cometh in the Name of the Lord.</p>
            <p>London, <hi>Printed by</hi> M. Inman, <hi>and are to be ſold a the</hi> Three Bibles in Pauls <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, and by</hi> Richard Moon, <hi>Bookſeller in</hi> Windſtreet <hi>in</hi> Briſtol. <hi>1660.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb facs="tcp:29825:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29825:2"/>
            <head>THE VVarnings of the Lorde To the Men of this GENERATION.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To <hi>OLIVER CROMWEL</hi> Protector, THESE. <hi>Friend,</hi> The <hi>Burden</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> upon <hi>me,</hi> for <hi>thee,</hi> is <hi>great,</hi> and the <hi>weight</hi> thereof <hi>heavy:</hi> Therefore in the <hi>Fear</hi> of <hi>God</hi> hear and conſider, for <hi>it</hi> doth concern <hi>thee.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>RT <hi>thou ſtill</hi> aſleep? Are <hi>thine</hi> eyes <hi>yet</hi> cloſed? and <hi>thine</hi> ears ſtopped? Will nothing awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>thee?</hi> Perceiveſt <hi>thou</hi> not that the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> is departed from <hi>thee,</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom</hi> from <hi>thy</hi> Counſels, and <hi>Spirit</hi> from <hi>thy</hi> men of <hi>War,</hi> and <hi>ſucceſs</hi> from <hi>thine</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings; and the <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>thee</hi> (that was once) from off the <hi>Nations?</hi> and the <hi>Magnificence</hi> and <hi>State</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> which whilſt the <hi>Lord</hi> was with <hi>it,</hi> ſtood with <hi>dread</hi> &amp; <hi>terror</hi> over the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> round about, <hi>ſinking</hi> down, and <hi>falling, languiſhing,</hi> and <hi>crumbling</hi> into the <hi>Duſt?</hi> How have the <hi>Men</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> who have been as <hi>ſtrong</hi> and <hi>fierce</hi> as <hi>Lions,</hi> as <hi>ſwift</hi> as <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pards,</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:29825:3"/> whom <hi>nothing</hi> could overcome <hi>whilſt their Rock was with them,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hiſpaniola.</hi> See the <hi>brief</hi> and <hi>perfe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Journal. &amp;c. by <hi>I. S.</hi> an <hi>Eye</hi> witneſs, where it is related how the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my conſiſting of <hi>ſome</hi> thouſands, <hi>fled</hi> before <hi>Fifty</hi> poor <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and could not be made to ſtand, no not ſo much as with <hi>their</hi> Major Gen. <hi>Heane,</hi> though <hi>he</hi> beſought them <hi>for God ſake;</hi> but left <hi>him</hi> alone to ſacrifice <hi>his</hi> life among the <hi>thickeſt</hi> of his Enemies, which <hi>he</hi> then did, who <hi>ſlew him,</hi> and <hi>ſix</hi> hundred of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> (beſides <hi>two hundred</hi> which <hi>crept</hi> into <hi>Buſhes,</hi> and were left behind in the <hi>woods,</hi> whom the <hi>Negroes</hi> and <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lattoes</hi> ſoon after diſpatched) and <hi>wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> near <hi>Three</hi> hundred, moſt of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutions being done in the <hi>back</hi> parts; and ſo returned weary with <hi>their ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terings,</hi> and laden with <hi>their Victory,</hi> to their Town of <hi>Domingo,</hi> of which, <hi>ſeven Engliſh</hi> Colours which they carryed with <hi>them,</hi> were the <hi>ſure</hi> Trophies. A <hi>plain</hi> demonſtration what <hi>men</hi> are when <hi>God forſakes them.</hi>
                  </note> fallen in the <hi>Day</hi> of <hi>Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle? At the rebuke of one,</hi> (as it were) how have a <hi>Thouſand</hi> of <hi>them</hi> fled? And at the <hi>rebuke</hi> of a <hi>few,</hi> how have <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands</hi> been put to flight, and the <hi>Carcaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> of <hi>many</hi> hundreds <hi>fallen</hi> to the <hi>ground? The children of Ephraim being armed, and carrying bows, turned back in the day of Battel?</hi> How <hi>heavily</hi> drives on <hi>thy expenſive</hi> and <hi>great</hi> expeditions at <hi>Sea?</hi> How <hi>vain</hi> and <hi>fruitleſs</hi> are <hi>they</hi> in <hi>their</hi> enterpriſes upon a<note n="†" place="margin">Spain.</note> 
                  <hi>Nation</hi> whom <hi>thou</hi> haſt <hi>diſdained,</hi> who were in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner at the <hi>ſoles</hi> of <hi>thy feet,</hi> whom <hi>thou</hi> thoughtſt to have <hi>ſwallowed</hi> up <hi>quick,</hi> and <hi>their power</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> to have <hi>weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> down in <hi>One</hi> day, who now <hi>defie thee,</hi> and <hi>thy</hi> ſtrength, and with <hi>no</hi> charge (in compariſon) <hi>walk</hi> up and down <hi>ſmiling,</hi> and as <hi>ſecure</hi> in <hi>their</hi> habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whilſt <hi>thou</hi> emptieſt <hi>thy</hi> Treaſures, and wearieſt out <hi>thy</hi> Fleets, without ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting upon <hi>them</hi> any <hi>conſiderable</hi> damage? How are the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> of <hi>this</hi> Nation, who were wont to <hi>run readily</hi> under <hi>thy</hi> Conduct, &amp; even <hi>rejoyced</hi> to hear of a <hi>Forreign</hi> Expedition, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially againſt the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> whom <hi>they</hi> always <hi>chaſtiſed,</hi> as <hi>they</hi> did of late <hi>Maſter</hi> down the <hi>Mightieſt</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The United Provinces Fleets.</note> Powers of the <hi>world</hi> at <hi>Sea,</hi> even then when <hi>they</hi> were but <hi>newly</hi> come out of a <hi>long</hi> and <hi>ſore inteſtine</hi> War, now become <hi>dead at the heart, lumps</hi> of <hi>fleſh,</hi> and <hi>averſe</hi> to <hi>War?</hi> How are the <hi>robbings</hi> and <hi>ſpoilings</hi> of the <hi>Merchants</hi> at <hi>their own</hi> doors, by an <hi>inconſiderable</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>crawled</hi> out of a<note n="*" place="margin">Dunkirk.</note> 
                  <hi>Hole</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> from whom <hi>thy</hi> Fleets have not ſecured <hi>them,</hi> exceeded in a <hi>ſhort</hi> time all that <hi>they</hi> ſuffered throughout the <hi>Dutch</hi> Engagements; and when <hi>ſome</hi> of <hi>thine</hi> have attached <hi>them,</hi> how have <hi>thoſe uncircumciſed</hi> come off with <hi>advantage,</hi> and over the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Captives have <hi>they</hi> not <hi>inſulted</hi> and <hi>vaunted, Of what Nation are ye? Ye are not Engliſh men; ye are not the People who fought with the Dutch.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:29825:3"/> The</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">See the King of <hi>Spain's</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the VVar.</note> 
                  <hi>Subjects of the King of Spain beat them off.</hi> How doth this <hi>once contemned</hi> Enemy <hi>diſtreſs thy</hi> Counſels, provoke <hi>thee</hi> to anger, and put <hi>thee</hi> to it, how to engage <hi>them?</hi> How do <hi>thy Taxes</hi> continue, and <hi>Trade</hi> decay, and the hearts of <hi>thy old</hi> Friends draw from <hi>thee,</hi> and <hi>thine</hi> Enemies hate and watch <hi>thee</hi> miſchief, and thirſt after <hi>thy</hi> deſtruction? And of what ſort of people can <hi>thy</hi> calm and moſt weighty thoughts give <hi>thee</hi> aſſurance of their ſtanding <hi>by thee,</hi> ſhould <hi>affliction</hi> from the <hi>Lord</hi> ariſe up againſt <hi>thee?</hi> Then <hi>thou</hi> wilt ſee the <hi>Guard</hi> gone, the <hi>Fence</hi> removed, the <hi>Preſence</hi> withdrawn, <hi>thy Horſes</hi> fleſh, and not ſpirit; <hi>thy men</hi> ſhadows, thy <hi>strength</hi> to ſit ſtill.</p>
               <p>Was it wont <hi>thus</hi> to be with <hi>thee?</hi> Did <hi>thy</hi> Sword (till of late) ever <hi>return empty from the blood of the ſlain, and the ſpoil of the Mighty?</hi> Could the <hi>ſpirit</hi> that was riſen up againſt the <hi>Lord</hi> in theſe <hi>three</hi> Nations, and the <hi>Dominions</hi> thereunto ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining, ſtand before <hi>thee?</hi> Was ever any thing <hi>too</hi> hard for <hi>thee?</hi> Miſſedſt <hi>thou</hi> in <hi>thy</hi> Counſels at any time? What e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>thou</hi> didſt put forth <hi>thine</hi> hand to do, was it not brought to paſs? Was not <hi>Wiſdom</hi> with <hi>thee,</hi> and <hi>Counſel as the Oracles of God?</hi> Of a <hi>little despiſed one,</hi> becameſt <hi>thou</hi> not <hi>as the Army</hi> of <hi>God?</hi> At <hi>thy</hi> feet did not the <hi>proudeſt</hi> enemy <hi>fall</hi> down and <hi>bow?</hi> Didſt not <hi>thou come upon Princes as upon Morter, and as the Petter treadeth the Clay?</hi> Were not the <hi>hearts</hi> of <hi>honeſt</hi> men <hi>knit</hi> to <hi>thee</hi> as <hi>one</hi> man? Was <hi>any</hi> thing <hi>ſo</hi> great that <hi>they</hi> could not entruſt <hi>thee</hi> with? Was <hi>any</hi> thing <hi>ſo</hi> dear that <hi>they</hi> were not ready to lay down for <hi>thy</hi> ſake? did <hi>they</hi> ſigh at any time at the remembrance of <hi>thee?</hi> Did <hi>their</hi> faces <hi>wax pale, confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> or <hi>covered?</hi> Or, was not the <hi>remembrance</hi> of <hi>thee</hi> to <hi>them ſweet</hi> and <hi>pleaſant,</hi> as <hi>the dew upon the tender Herb, as life from the dead,</hi> as of <hi>him that took off the yoke on their Jaws, that remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the burthen from off the ſhoulder, that relieved the oppreſſed, that delivered the poor from him that was too strong for him?</hi> Waſt not <hi>thou</hi> a <hi>dread</hi> and <hi>terror</hi> to the <hi>world</hi> abroad? Was it <hi>ever</hi> ſo with <hi>man</hi> in <hi>theſe</hi> later Generations, as it was with <hi>thee</hi> whilſt <hi>God</hi> was with <hi>thee, whilst the Rock had not forſaken thee?</hi> Is it not time for <hi>thee</hi> to <hi>conſider,</hi> and <hi>lay to heart?</hi> How canſt <hi>thou</hi> ſleep? How canſt <hi>thou</hi> ſuffer <hi>thine</hi> eye-lids to give <hi>thee</hi> any ſlumber, whileſt it is <hi>thus</hi> with <hi>thee?</hi> Be <hi>still</hi> therefore, and <hi>cool,</hi> and let the <hi>witneſs of God</hi> in <hi>thee,</hi> ſearch and try <hi>thee,</hi> and hear <hi>thou</hi> what <hi>it</hi> ſaith in <hi>this</hi> thing.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:29825:4"/>
               <p>Did not the <hi>Lord</hi> hear the <hi>groans</hi> of <hi>thoſe</hi> who ſuffered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of <hi>their</hi> Conſciences in the <hi>dayes</hi> of the <hi>Biſhops?</hi> Pull'd he not up <hi>that</hi> generation in <hi>his</hi> anger? Swept <hi>he</hi> not away the <hi>Powers</hi> that ſupported <hi>them,</hi> in <hi>his ſore</hi> diſpleaſure, though of <hi>many hundred years ſtanding?</hi> And when the <hi>ſame</hi> ſpirit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe more <hi>exceeding</hi> fierce in <hi>another</hi> form, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> thereby taking in to the former the <hi>Nation</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the <hi>multitudes</hi> of the <hi>ſame Faction</hi> in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> who <hi>ſuffered</hi> by, and <hi>oppoſed it</hi> in <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and <hi>fought</hi> againſt <hi>it</hi> in <hi>Monarchy?</hi> Lop't <hi>he</hi> not down <hi>thoſe lofty Boughs with terror?</hi> Became <hi>he</hi> not <hi>terrible</hi> to the <hi>men of high ſtature?</hi> And <hi>when</hi> at length <hi>he</hi> had drawn <hi>them</hi> together as <hi>into a pit,</hi> braked <hi>he</hi> not in upon <hi>them</hi> with a <hi>furious</hi> blow of <hi>horror</hi> and <hi>amazement?</hi> And did <hi>he</hi> not ſmite <hi>them</hi> with a <hi>wound incurable, they</hi> &amp; <hi>their</hi> King, and <hi>their</hi> Nobles; <hi>their</hi> mighty <hi>men</hi> of <hi>war, their</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Counſellors, <hi>their</hi> Prieſts and <hi>their</hi> Officers, <hi>their</hi> Horſes, with <hi>thoſe</hi> that ſate thereon, and <hi>their</hi> whole ſtrength, leaving <hi>their</hi> Name an <hi>aſtoniſhment</hi> and a <hi>wonder,</hi> and a <hi>curſe</hi> unto <hi>poſterity;</hi> giving <hi>this</hi> later generation in which <hi>this</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit appeared, onely <hi>ſo</hi> much time as to ſhew what <hi>they</hi> would do to <hi>Us</hi> for <hi>our conſciences,</hi> could <hi>they</hi> have but gotten <hi>power</hi> in <hi>their</hi> hands to have brought <hi>it</hi> to paſs.</p>
               <p>Was't not <hi>Thou</hi> one who <hi>ſuffered</hi> and <hi>groaned</hi> in <hi>thoſe</hi> days? waſt not <hi>Thou</hi> principally <hi>hated, deſpiſed,</hi> and <hi>ſought</hi> to be <hi>cut off</hi> with the reſt of us, then whom, <hi>never</hi> was a generation <hi>more contemned,</hi> and <hi>ſcorned,</hi> and <hi>reproached,</hi> and <hi>maligned,</hi> and <hi>thirſted</hi> after, to be <hi>rooted</hi> up from off the <hi>face</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> nor <hi>more unlikely</hi> (as to men) to carry the <hi>Day</hi> againſt <hi>ſuch</hi> Powers of <hi>three ſuch</hi> Nations? Waſt not <hi>thou</hi> the <hi>man</hi> who didſt bear, as on a <hi>common</hi> ſhoulder, the <hi>ſufferings</hi> of the <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed</hi> for <hi>conſcience</hi> ſake, who with <hi>thee</hi> were <hi>appointed to the ſame deſtruction?</hi> Went not <hi>then</hi> every <hi>ſuch ſuffering</hi> to <hi>thine</hi> own <hi>heart?</hi> Felt not <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u</hi> every <hi>one</hi> of them on <hi>thine</hi> own ſhoulder? Couldſt not <hi>thou</hi> have laid down <hi>thy</hi> life for <hi>one</hi> of <hi>them?</hi> How <hi>tender</hi> was <hi>(then) thine</hi> heart? How <hi>ſounding thy</hi> bowels? Therefore <hi>flowed</hi> not <hi>in</hi> the <hi>hearts</hi> of <hi>them</hi> all to <hi>thee?</hi> In <hi>them</hi> and <hi>thee,</hi> was there not <hi>one</hi> Spirit, and <hi>one</hi> heart? For <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> cauſe did not the <hi>Lord</hi> call <hi>thee,</hi> and raiſe <hi>thee</hi> up to head <hi>his</hi> Armies? Made <hi>he</hi> not <hi>thee his</hi> Sword? Did <hi>he</hi> not execute
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29825:4"/> by <hi>thee, his</hi> vengeance upon <hi>thoſe</hi> Generations? And as <hi>thou</hi> returnedſt laden with <hi>Victories</hi> in <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> was not <hi>this</hi> the <hi>burthen</hi> of <hi>thy</hi> Letters and Declarations to the <hi>Parliament</hi> and Nation, <hi>LIBERTY of CONSCIENCE?</hi> Were not <hi>thy</hi> Speeches in <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Council,</hi> and where e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>thou</hi> cameſt, in the <hi>behalf</hi> of <hi>tender Conſciences?</hi> Came not <hi>it</hi> from <hi>thee</hi> in <hi>thy</hi> Letters, Declarations, and ſpeeches, with <hi>ſuch</hi> weight and heavineſs, as manifeſted <hi>thee</hi> a <hi>man pained</hi> at the <hi>very</hi> heart, and in a <hi>continued travel of ſoul</hi> for <hi>it,</hi> and <hi>bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs</hi> of <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and as <hi>one</hi> whoſe <hi>very</hi> life was oppreſſed? Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dedſt <hi>thou</hi> not through the <hi>Blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d</hi> and <hi>War,</hi> the <hi>difficulties</hi> and <hi>temptation,</hi> the <hi>hardſhips</hi> and <hi>dangers</hi> of <hi>three ſuch</hi> Nations, <hi>ſo</hi> divided, and in Factions, with a <hi>reſtleſs</hi> and an <hi>unwearied</hi> ſpirit, till <hi>it</hi> was <hi>eaſed</hi> in the <hi>total</hi> overthrow of the <hi>conjoined</hi> ſtrength of <hi>all thoſe</hi> in <hi>whom that</hi> ſpirit <hi>appeared</hi> and <hi>acted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whileſt it was <hi>thus</hi> with <hi>thee,</hi> did the <hi>Lord</hi> ever fail or forſake <hi>thee?</hi> Or wantedſt <hi>thou</hi> the <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>hands</hi> of the <hi>honest</hi> men of <hi>theſe</hi> Nations? Needed what <hi>thou</hi> declaredſt and ſpakeſt <hi>(thou)</hi> an <hi>Interpreter?</hi> Was <hi>it</hi> to <hi>them</hi> in an <hi>unknown</hi> Language? Can the <hi>generations</hi> that are paſt, produce the like, of the <hi>Lord's</hi> and <hi>his</hi> people being with a <hi>man,</hi> as with <hi>Thee?</hi> VVas it not <hi>thus</hi> with <hi>thee</hi> whileſt <hi>thy</hi> heart was <hi>tender, pleading</hi> the <hi>cauſe</hi> of the <hi>Lords Oppreſſed?</hi> and of <hi>his Kingdom in the conſciences of men,</hi> which <hi>thou</hi> looked <hi>it</hi> upon as <hi>near at hand,</hi> and often haſt expreſt <hi>it</hi> in <hi>word, Declaration,</hi> and <hi>Letter,</hi> to be the <hi>deſign</hi> and <hi>end</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> in the <hi>wars,</hi> to ſet <hi>it</hi> up? Was <hi>ever mans</hi> words in <hi>that</hi> day, like <hi>thine,</hi> in relation here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto? And was <hi>it</hi> not <hi>thine own</hi> obſervation often, <hi>That as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny party of men in the Parliament roſe up to make Laws againſt it, and ſo to limit the spirit of the Lord, it was a ſure and certain ſymptom and fore-runner of their being broken in pieces, and of all that were with them in spirit and aſſiſtance.</hi> And did not the <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving</hi> and <hi>ſeeing</hi> of <hi>this,</hi> become <hi>ſtrength</hi> in <hi>thee</hi> to oppoſe <hi>them?</hi> Did <hi>it</hi> not carry <hi>thee</hi> thorough the <hi>difficulties</hi> that <hi>thou</hi> kneweſt <hi>thou</hi> ſhouldſt meet withall <hi>therein,</hi> which to <hi>outward</hi> conſideration <hi>ſeemed impoſſible</hi> to be <hi>encountered</hi> with and <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come?</hi> And <hi>become it not</hi> the <hi>over<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hrown of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll that attempted it?</hi> Haſt not <hi>Thou</hi> ſeen <hi>this</hi> with <hi>thine</hi> eye, and compaſſed <hi>it</hi> in <hi>thine</hi> heart, and effected <hi>it</hi> with <hi>Thine</hi> hand? <hi>Call to minde the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29825:5"/> former dayes, and let the things that are paſt, come into thy remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance?</hi> And ſince <hi>all</hi> power was in <hi>thine</hi> hand, haſt <hi>thou</hi> not<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>O. C.</hi> Speech to the <hi>little</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the <hi>Council-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> at <hi>VVhite-hall, Iuly</hi> 4. 1653. Page 25.</note> expreſt <hi>thy</hi> ſelf that <hi>thou</hi> thoughteſt <hi>ſomething was at the door of that good we waited for,</hi> that <hi>we</hi> were <hi>at the edge of the promiſes and propheſies; not vainly looking on that propheſie in</hi> Daniel, <hi>And the Kingdom ſhall not be delivered to another people;</hi> and ſaidſt, <hi>thou didſt thank God thou hadſt thy hopes exerciſed in theſe things:</hi> And to make way for <hi>that,</hi> didſt <hi>thou</hi> not place the <hi>ground</hi> of the <hi>alterations</hi> and <hi>changes thou</hi> haſt made? And haſt <hi>thou</hi> not ſaid, That<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>O P.</hi> Speech to the <hi>Parliament</hi> in the <hi>Painted Chamber, Sep.</hi> 12. 1654. <hi>Pag.</hi> 30, 31. Pag. 36, 37.</note> 
                  <hi>Liberty of Conſcience is a natural Right?</hi> That <hi>it is one of the four Fundamentals of the Government thou</hi> hadſt ſet up, as the <hi>iſſue of all theſe Wars, for which things ſake the Powers of the Government were taken up; and might that be ſecure, thou couldeſt be contented to lay them down again: But rather then to give thy conſent to the wilful throwing away thereof, and that in relation to the good of theſe Nations and Poſterity, thou couldſt ſooner be willing to be rolled into thy Grave, and buryed with Infamy:</hi> That, <hi>had it not been for the hopes of Liberty of Conſcience,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag 31.</note> 
                  <hi>all the Money in the Nation would not have tempted men to fight upon ſuch an account as they have enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; and otherwiſe to do, was no part of the Contest with the Common Adverſary:</hi> With <hi>much</hi> more of the <hi>like</hi> nature conteined in <hi>thy</hi> Speeches to the <hi>ſhort,</hi> and the <hi>late</hi> Parliament, and to <hi>others</hi> upon occaſion, as <hi>full</hi> and <hi>ſignificant</hi> as need to be in <hi>ſuch</hi> a thing, or can be <hi>well</hi> expreſſed.</p>
               <p>But hath it proved according to what <hi>thou</hi> haſt <hi>ſo</hi> ſaid to <hi>thoſe</hi> who are come to witneſs the <hi>Seed</hi> of the <hi>Eternal God rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> &amp; <hi>raiſing</hi> up in <hi>them, (which is come to, and muſt reign for ever &amp; ever; to make way for the reign of which, was all the late Wars and battels of Blood?)</hi> Hath <hi>thine</hi> heart and <hi>thine</hi> actions, (ſince <hi>all</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer hath been in <hi>thine</hi> hand) been towards <hi>ſuch</hi> as it was <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> the <hi>Wars</hi> were ended, or as <hi>thou</hi> haſt <hi>ſince</hi> expreſſed? Are there <hi>any</hi> that have, and do <hi>groan</hi> for <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> that <hi>ſuffer</hi> becauſe of <hi>it</hi> in theſe Dominions? Let the <hi>Priſons</hi> in <hi>most</hi> parts of the <hi>Nation,</hi> the <hi>cruel mockings</hi> and <hi>ſtonings,</hi> and <hi>whippings,</hi> and <hi>beatings,</hi> and <hi>ſtockings;</hi> the <hi>tumults</hi> and <hi>inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> the <hi>finings,</hi> and <hi>long</hi> and <hi>ſore impriſonments</hi> in <hi>heat</hi> and <hi>cold,</hi> in <hi>hunger</hi> and <hi>nakedneſs,</hi> ſhut up from <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Relations,</hi> and the <hi>wholeſome</hi> air, and <hi>conveniences</hi> of <hi>Livelihood;</hi> the <hi>inhumane</hi> and <hi>barbarous</hi> uſages, without regard to <hi>ages</hi> or <hi>ſexes, young</hi> or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29825:5"/> 
                  <hi>old, children,</hi> or the <hi>hoary-headed men</hi> or <hi>women,</hi> ſome of <hi>which</hi> not fit to be related to <hi>modeſt</hi> ears, without <hi>mercy, reaſon,</hi> or <hi>compaſſion,</hi> declare and ſpeak: together with the <hi>filthy</hi> dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, &amp; <hi>noiſome</hi> holes, &amp; <hi>cloſe</hi> vaults, and the <hi>ſpoiling</hi> of <hi>their</hi> goods, with <hi>many</hi> more <hi>ſore</hi> and <hi>cruel</hi> ſufferings undergone by <hi>many hundreds</hi> for <hi>conſcience ſake,</hi> ſince, and within the time of <hi>thy</hi> Rule and Government, who have been <hi>as</hi> faithful <hi>as</hi> any, to the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> and <hi>as much</hi> (in <hi>their</hi> places) have <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone,</hi> and <hi>fought</hi> for <hi>it</hi> and <hi>Thee;</hi> Some for <hi>reproving</hi> of <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>iniquity</hi> in the <hi>Streets</hi> and <hi>Market</hi>-places; ſome for <hi>bidding peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple fear the Lord; ſome</hi> for <hi>giving</hi> out a <hi>Paper</hi> in <hi>compaſſion</hi> to the <hi>ignorant,</hi> directing them the <hi>way to Salvation</hi> in the words of the <hi>Scripture:</hi> Some for <hi>declaring</hi> againſt <hi>Deceit,</hi> and <hi>witneſſing</hi> againſt the <hi>changeable</hi> Prieſthood, <hi>(against whom thou haſt had a Teſtimony)</hi> as <hi>they</hi> have been <hi>moved</hi> of the <hi>Lord:</hi> Some for that in <hi>Conſcience they</hi> cannot <hi>reſpect the perſons of men,</hi> nor <hi>ſwear,</hi> nor <hi>pay Tythes,</hi> (which <hi>Thou</hi> &amp; the <hi>Army</hi> have <hi>ſo often</hi> &amp; <hi>long</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plained of, even to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> as a <hi>ſore Grievance,</hi> remind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>them</hi> thereof, with other things, by a Petition according (as <hi>Thou</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>O. C.</hi> ſpeech to the <hi>little</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the <hi>Council-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> at <hi>VVhite-hall, Iuly</hi> 4. 1653. <hi>Pag.</hi> 7.</note> ſaidſt) <hi>ye thought it was your Duty, who had many deſires and thirſtings in your Spirits, to find out wayes and means upon your return from the Wars, being fully bent to find out ways &amp; means for the Nation to reap the fruit of all the Blood and Treaſure that had been expended in this Cauſe.</hi> And becauſe nothing was done as to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars in <hi>that</hi> Petition, but <hi>words, thou</hi> reckonedſt that up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Long</hi> to the <hi>Little</hi> Parliament.) Nor <hi>pay</hi> the <hi>unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable</hi> Fees of <hi>Jaylors,</hi> where <hi>they</hi> have not offended, nor <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge themſelves</hi> tranſgreſſors where <hi>they</hi> are <hi>innocent,</hi> nor <hi>bring themſelves</hi> under <hi>Engagements,</hi> who are not <hi>their</hi> own, nor guided by <hi>their</hi> own, but by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>Lord;</hi> nor <hi>conform</hi> to the <hi>Faſhions</hi> and <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> of the <hi>world:</hi> Some for <hi>coming</hi> to <hi>viſite their</hi> Friends and Relations in <hi>Priſon.</hi> Some have been <hi>taken</hi> out of <hi>their</hi> peaceable Meetings <hi>waiting</hi> on the <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>caſt</hi> into <hi>Priſon;</hi> ſome for <hi>having ſuch Meetings</hi> in <hi>their</hi> Houſes; ſome <hi>taken</hi> up in the <hi>Streets</hi> as they have <hi>paſſed quietly</hi> along, neither <hi>ſaying,</hi> nor <hi>doing any thing;</hi> ſome out of <hi>their Innes</hi> and <hi>Chambers;</hi> ſome for <hi>refuſing</hi> to <hi>take</hi> the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Abjuration,</hi> out of <hi>Conſcience</hi> to an <hi>Oath;</hi> ſome for <hi>going about doing good,</hi> (as did <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth, whom God annointed with the Holy Ghoſt and with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29825:6"/> power, who ſo went about all the Cities and Villages</hi>) at <hi>his</hi> Command. The time would fail to inſtance <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Caſes</hi> and the <hi>Sufferings</hi> as to each, a <hi>Volume</hi> would not contain <hi>them:</hi> The <hi>Preſidents</hi> of <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Records</hi> in <hi>this</hi> Nation (all things conſidered) will not paralel <hi>them:</hi> The <hi>ears</hi> will <hi>tingle</hi> of <hi>all</hi> that hear <hi>all</hi> that hath been inflicted <hi>herein</hi> by <hi>Judges, Juſtices, Officers,</hi> the <hi>rude</hi> multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, <hi>Jaylors, Thieves</hi> and <hi>Murtherers,</hi> amongſt whom <hi>they have been numbred</hi> and <hi>caſt,</hi> contrary unto, and in the overthrow of <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> wherein, and whereby divers of <hi>them have ſuffered the loſs of their lives;</hi> and <hi>many</hi> more had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhed, but that the <hi>life</hi> of the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which <hi>they witneſſed,</hi> and for which <hi>they</hi> ſuffered, preſerved <hi>them</hi> alive beyond the poſſibility of Creature-expectations, haveing lain in <hi>priſon</hi> after the manner aforeſaid, ſome <hi>many Months,</hi> ſome a <hi>Yeare,</hi> ſome above <hi>two years;</hi> yea<note n="*" place="margin">At a <hi>Meeting</hi> near <hi>Northamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> where this was done by order (as was ſaid) of <hi>Major Butler,</hi> then called a <hi>Maj. Gen.</hi> &amp; the <hi>man</hi> whoſe ground it was where the <hi>Meeting</hi> was kept, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding <hi>this</hi> Treſpaſs upon <hi>gim,</hi> and <hi>outrae.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>thy Troopers have rod in with their hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> upon <hi>men</hi> and <hi>women,</hi> as <hi>they have been praying on their knees to the Lord</hi> in <hi>their peaceable</hi> Meetings, and <hi>violently</hi> have pul'd<note n="†" place="margin">VVilliam Deusbury, <hi>a</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter <hi>of the</hi> everlaſting Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</note> 
                  <hi>him away, who was ſpeaking to the Lord in Prayer upon his knees a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them,</hi> (a <hi>cruel</hi> unmanlineſs, <hi>never</hi> heard of before this <hi>thy</hi> Day; and on others who are innocent, have <hi>thy</hi> Souldiers been<note n="*" place="margin">Miles Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, <hi>and</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Salthouſe, <hi>at</hi> Exeter, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>long</hi> and <hi>inhumane Guards,</hi> keeping <hi>them cloſe</hi> Priſoners, and impriſoning <hi>thoſe</hi> who come to <hi>viſite them,</hi> contrary to <hi>all Law, Equity, Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>common Humanity;</hi> yea, ſome have had<note n="†" place="margin">In the <hi>North</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Piſtols</hi> preſented to <hi>their</hi> mouths, by the <hi>Troopers,</hi> hall'd out of <hi>their</hi> Meetings, and with <hi>blaſphemous</hi> dammings have the <hi>Troopers</hi> ſworn that there <hi>they</hi> ſhould <hi>dye</hi> if <hi>they</hi> did not deity <hi>their</hi> Religion, and ſome have <hi>they</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The <hi>Lord</hi> healed the wound <hi>mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly,</hi> as it was made <hi>bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>run through the Arm</hi> for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to <hi>deny the Lord that bought them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And of <hi>many</hi> of <hi>theſe</hi> things <hi>thou</hi> haſt not been ignorant, for the <hi>Lord,</hi> (who delivered <hi>thee</hi> out of <hi>all thy</hi> troubles and difficulties, and was <hi>thine</hi> Arm and Counſellor when <hi>thou</hi> waſt the inſtrument of <hi>his</hi> indignation on thoſe who did and would have <hi>done</hi> ſome <hi>ſuch</hi> things as <hi>theſe</hi>) hath <hi>riſing early,</hi> moved and ſent <hi>many</hi> of <hi>his</hi> Servants and Handmaids from <hi>moſt</hi> parts of the <hi>Nation</hi> to <hi>thee, Meſſenger</hi> upon <hi>Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> and <hi>Teſtimony</hi> upon <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> who in <hi>his</hi> fear and dread have laid <hi>many</hi> of <hi>theſe</hi> things before <hi>thee,</hi> ſome in <hi>Writings,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by <hi>Verbal</hi> Declaration; and from <hi>his</hi> mouth hath <hi>he</hi> by <hi>them often</hi> warned <hi>thee</hi> of <hi>his</hi> diſpleaſure, and the fury of <hi>his</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:29825:6"/> jealouſie, which is waxing hot againſt <hi>thee,</hi> becauſe thereof; yea, <hi>thy</hi> warnings have exceeded whatever man had before <hi>thee,</hi> as have <hi>thy</hi> mercies; And to <hi>that of God</hi> in <hi>thee</hi> have ſome of <hi>them</hi> reached, and the <hi>burthens many</hi> of <hi>them</hi> have born for <hi>thee,</hi> have been <hi>great,</hi> and the <hi>ſounding</hi> of <hi>their</hi> bowels that <hi>thou</hi> mighteſt hear, and be deliverered from the <hi>wrath</hi> which is <hi>coming,</hi> and <hi>haſteneth</hi> a-pace; and the <hi>long-ſuffering</hi> and <hi>patience</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>his</hi> people, hath been <hi>much</hi> to <hi>thee,</hi> and <hi>his</hi> compaſſion not willing that <hi>thou</hi> ſhouldeſt <hi>die,</hi> but <hi>hear</hi> and <hi>live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But haſt <hi>thou</hi> heard? Haſt <hi>thou</hi> delivered <hi>the poor out of the hands of him who is too ſtrong for him?</hi> Haſt <hi>thou broken the unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous bonds?</hi> Haſt <hi>thou delivered the priſoner,</hi> and <hi>eaſed the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed?</hi> Haſt <hi>thou been the ſword of God</hi> upon <hi>their</hi> oppreſſors? Or, a <hi>Protector</hi> of <hi>them,</hi> who for <hi>witneſſing of his name ſuffer wrong?</hi> Are the <hi>priſons</hi> clear? Hath <hi>care</hi> been taken that the <hi>innocent</hi> ſuffer not for <hi>conſcience</hi> ſake; as <hi>there</hi> hath been of <hi>ſpeaking</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring</hi> thereof in the <hi>Government?</hi> Hath <hi>one</hi> offender in <hi>theſe</hi> caſes been <hi>made exemplary</hi> by <hi>thee?</hi> Or, hath ſo much as <hi>one cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> Jailor been by <hi>thy</hi> order puniſhed? Or, are not <hi>theſe</hi> things done, and continued to be done in <hi>thy</hi> Name, and by <hi>thy</hi> Authority, and under <hi>thy</hi> Government? And for thy uſe are not <hi>thoſe</hi> Fines impoſed? Hath not <hi>thy</hi> Proclamations gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven encouragement for what is done? Haſt not <hi>thou</hi> been told that <hi>thoſe</hi> who do <hi>theſe</hi> things, have ſaid, <hi>they</hi> have done them <hi>by</hi> authority from <hi>thee</hi> and <hi>thy</hi> Officers? Haſt <hi>thou</hi> taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice thereof, when <hi>it</hi> hath been <hi>ſo</hi> told <hi>thee? Wer't thou clear, wouldſt thou let it lye upon thee?</hi> Do not <hi>underſtanding</hi> men know, that if it were not <hi>thus</hi> with <hi>thee, ſuch</hi> things <hi>dare</hi> not to bee done in <hi>theſe</hi> Nations? Is it not plain to <hi>all</hi> that are <hi>reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> that <hi>thou,</hi> who carriedſt <hi>it</hi> through ſo <hi>many years</hi> wars and difficulties even againſt <hi>ſome</hi> of the <hi>Powers</hi> that ruled, canſt ſurely preſerve <hi>it</hi> now <hi>thou</hi> haſt <hi>all</hi> Power, and <hi>art in peace with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe Dominions,</hi> did <hi>that</hi> ſpirit rule <hi>thee now,</hi> which, for <hi>it,</hi> carried <hi>thee</hi> through <hi>ſuch</hi> warrs and difficulties? <hi>Charles Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>art</hi> could have put off from <hi>himſelf</hi> the <hi>ſufferings</hi> of the <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> on the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and have alleged that <hi>they</hi> were a <hi>non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable, factious</hi> Generation, who diſturbed <hi>uniformity</hi> in the <hi>Nation,</hi> &amp; <hi>did</hi> contrary to the <hi>Law;</hi> But <hi>that</hi> would not excuſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29825:7"/> 
                  <hi>him,</hi> nor <hi>his</hi> ſtanding ſtill, and looking on, whilſt <hi>he</hi> had power to remedy <hi>it,</hi> but did not, nor that thoſe <hi>Laws</hi> were of <hi>long</hi> ſtanding; nor the <hi>diſ-affection</hi> of the <hi>Great men,</hi> and <hi>Nobles,</hi> and <hi>Rulers,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and the <hi>generality</hi> of the <hi>Nation</hi> to <hi>that</hi> way from the <hi>Judgement</hi> of <hi>God, which hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken hold on Him, and his Children, and his Party,</hi> whom he hath made a <hi>dreadful</hi> example of <hi>his</hi> vengeance, and that by <hi>thy ſword</hi> as an <hi>inſtrument.</hi> But the <hi>caſe</hi> between <hi>thee</hi> and <hi>us</hi> is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe; <hi>no</hi> Law have <hi>we</hi> tranſgreſſed, except <hi>thou</hi> wilt have <hi>Maryes</hi> Law, which was <hi>made</hi> for, and <hi>guarded</hi> the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> to ſtand, and that for <hi>treble damages</hi> for <hi>Tythes.</hi> The <hi>righteous</hi> ends of the <hi>Warrs,</hi> in which <hi>we</hi> have born our part in the <hi>heat of the day,</hi> and <hi>thy</hi> Speeches and Government, (as hath been ſaid) ſay otherwiſe; <hi>We</hi> have been <hi>experienced ſufficiently</hi> the <hi>Common-wealths</hi> and <hi>thy</hi> friends whom <hi>no tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation,</hi> nor <hi>difficulty,</hi> nor danger could turn <hi>us</hi> from; nor for <hi>it</hi> and <hi>thee</hi> were <hi>our lives, or any thing we had dear;</hi> which <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> had <hi>never</hi> opportunity to underſtand by the <hi>Puritans,</hi> but through the <hi>glaſs</hi> of <hi>prejudice he alwaies beheld, thought,</hi> and <hi>judged them his real enemies:</hi> nor were <hi>they</hi> and <hi>he ever one</hi> in <hi>principle, ſpirit,</hi> and <hi>action,</hi> eſpcially in <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>one,</hi> and in <hi>ſuch</hi> action as <hi>thou</hi> and <hi>we</hi> have been, being the <hi>higheſt</hi> on which <hi>men</hi> were <hi>ever</hi> engaged in the <hi>field;</hi> the <hi>neareſt,</hi> and in the <hi>greateſt</hi> engagements: Yet do <hi>we</hi> (thus) ſuffer at <hi>thine</hi> hands, whom <hi>we have loved above any man;</hi> whoſe, with <hi>all</hi> that is dear to <hi>us</hi> have <hi>we</hi> become, and <hi>thy</hi> lot and portion have <hi>we</hi> cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, to ſtand or fall, as it ſhould be unto <hi>thee;</hi> and ſo have <hi>we</hi> ſtood by <hi>thee</hi> againſt <hi>all thine</hi> oppoſers, whether in <hi>field</hi> or <hi>Council. Thine</hi> enemies <hi>we</hi> have accounted and made <hi>our</hi> own, and never left <hi>thee,</hi> till <hi>thou</hi> waſt brought through <hi>all.</hi> And under <hi>thy</hi> Government, though <hi>ſpeaking</hi> as aforeſaid, in the <hi>behalf</hi> of <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> are <hi>we</hi> (who through the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable</hi> love of the <hi>Father</hi> are come to <hi>witneſſe the end of the Wars, the Son of God made manfeſt in our mortal fleſh, whoſe is the Kingdom, and the glory and the Dominion for ever;</hi> even his immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſeed raiſed, &amp; raiſing up in <hi>us,</hi> by which <hi>we</hi> are brought to <hi>testifie</hi> againſt the <hi>world,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Deceivers</hi> therein; and againſt the <hi>Faſhions</hi> and <hi>Cuſtoms,</hi> and <hi>works</hi> and <hi>deeds</hi> thereof, that <hi>they</hi> are evil as by <hi>his</hi> Light <hi>we</hi> have been ſhewn, and by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29825:7"/> 
                  <hi>his</hi> blood redeemed there-from in <hi>our</hi> own particulars) <hi>made the ſcorn and prey of all men;</hi> and have <hi>we</hi> ſuffered as aforeſaid, by the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>this</hi> world ruling in <hi>them,</hi> and now riſen up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>his</hi> annointed, who <hi>by the brightneſſe of his coming it</hi> knows doth, and is come to deſtroy <hi>it.</hi> And deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up are <hi>we</hi> into the <hi>wills,</hi> and <hi>luſts,</hi> and <hi>hands</hi> of <hi>our</hi> Enemies, of <hi>Malignant, Neutral, Impeached, Secluded,</hi> and <hi>other Judges, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices,</hi> and <hi>Officers,</hi> and of the <hi>rude</hi> multitude, even of the <hi>moſt unreaſonable</hi> and <hi>baſeſt</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> whom <hi>we</hi> have <hi>fought againſt,</hi> and <hi>overcome</hi> in the <hi>field,</hi> and <hi>totally</hi> overthrown, who <hi>now diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorge themſelves</hi> of the <hi>deadly</hi> malice and enmity <hi>they</hi> contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>then</hi> againſt <hi>us</hi> in the <hi>illegal</hi> and <hi>cruel</hi> uſages aforeſaid, for, and upon occaſion of the <hi>exerciſe of our Conſcience,</hi> who when the <hi>wars</hi> were <hi>ended</hi> for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> had <hi>little</hi> reaſon to expect <hi>ſuch</hi> dealing as <hi>we</hi> now receive from <hi>ſuch</hi> a Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who by the <hi>Sword</hi> ſought to have cut <hi>thee</hi> and <hi>us</hi> off for <hi>our Conſciences,</hi> But were overthrown, and <hi>this after</hi> that for <hi>theſe</hi> things ſake <hi>we</hi> were over <hi>them Victors</hi> and <hi>Conquerors;</hi> Or <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>Day</hi> as <hi>this</hi> had <hi>we</hi> cauſe to look for, eſpecially at <hi>thy</hi> hands, and under <hi>thy</hi> Government, whom the <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Hoſts,</hi> the <hi>jealous God,</hi> the <hi>God of theſe his ſuffering People,</hi> hath <hi>now</hi> tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and proved, to ſee what a one <hi>thou</hi> wouldſt be, and what <hi>thou</hi> wouldſt do, who didſt <hi>ſo</hi> vow and promiſe to <hi>him</hi> in the <hi>Day</hi> of <hi>thy</hi> diſtreſs, when <hi>He</hi> ſhould have delivered <hi>thee:</hi> And therefore hath <hi>He</hi> let <hi>thee</hi> remove <hi>all</hi> out of the way, whether <hi>Enemy</hi> or <hi>Powers,</hi> that <hi>thou mighteſt be without excuſe; No</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Government haſt <hi>thou now</hi> to wreſtle withall, or to complain of as <hi>thy</hi> hindrance in <hi>this</hi> particular; or <hi>Faction</hi> therein, or <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> or <hi>Nation</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or <hi>City</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> or <hi>Dominion</hi> of <hi>Ireland:</hi> And in <hi>his</hi> mighty Power hath <hi>he</hi> made <hi>ſtrong</hi> his <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> and armed hath <hi>he them</hi> with <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible</hi> and <hi>unheard</hi> of patience, to bear, endure, and ſuffer <hi>ſo,</hi> and in <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>manner,</hi> and by <hi>ſuch hands,</hi> and in <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>ſeaſon</hi> as hath been ſaid; ſome of whom <hi>now</hi> ſuffering, have a <hi>witneſs</hi> in <hi>thee,</hi> that <hi>they</hi> are <hi>dear</hi> and <hi>precious</hi> to the <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>innocent:</hi> And now art <hi>thou</hi> proved, art <hi>thou</hi> tryed and <hi>weighed in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance;</hi> behold the fruits <hi>thou</hi> haſt brought forth, which <hi>the day doth make manifeſt,</hi> according unto which canſt <hi>thou</hi> otherwiſe expect then to have <hi>thy</hi> reward from the <hi>Juſt</hi> and <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29825:8"/> God,</hi> whom in requital of <hi>all his Love</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> and <hi>Long-ſuffering</hi> to <hi>thee, thou</hi> haſt <hi>(thus)</hi> dealt withall in <hi>his</hi> ſeed, unto <hi>whom whatſoever</hi> hath been <hi>done,</hi> hath been <hi>done</hi> unto <hi>him, who will reward every man according to his deeds.</hi> Remember what <hi>thou</hi> ſaidſt to <hi>me</hi> at the <hi>Cock-Pit,</hi> about ſix Months before the <hi>Long Parliament</hi> was <hi>broken,</hi> viz. <hi>What ever men think and ſay of me, yet the end will make it to appear, That I have nothing in mine eye but the glory of God, and the good of theſe Nations: And if in mine old Age through my folly, I ſhall ſpill all theſe Mercies on the ground the Lord hath ſhewn me, know this, God will not bleſſe me</hi>—Now to <hi>that</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>thy</hi> Conſcience, the <hi>meaſure</hi> of him which <hi>thou</hi> haſt, in <hi>his</hi> fear and dread conſider, and let <hi>it</hi> ſearch and try <hi>thee;</hi> Haſt <hi>thou</hi> ſpilt on the ground (now in the time that <hi>gray hairs</hi> are coming upon <hi>thee</hi>) the <hi>Mercies</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> hath ſhewn <hi>thee</hi> in <hi>thy</hi> former <hi>dayes,</hi> yea or nay? <hi>Doth God bleſſe thee?</hi> Let <hi>his</hi> Witneſs in <hi>thee</hi> be heard to ſpeak and anſwer. Art <hi>thou (whoſe</hi> heart <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Sufferings</hi> aforeſaid do not <hi>now</hi> melt) in the <hi>ſame</hi> ſpirit as <hi>thou</hi> waſt in 1645. wherein <hi>thou</hi> waſt ready to have hazarded <hi>thy</hi> life and <hi>thine</hi> intereſts, <hi>on ſuch a caſe for to have remedied,</hi> ſuch was then <hi>thy</hi> tenderneſs, and ſenſe, and bowels? (And yet what were the <hi>ſufferings</hi> by the <hi>Biſhops</hi> in <hi>compariſon</hi> of <hi>theſe?</hi>) Or art not <hi>thou</hi> gone out of that which made and preſerved <hi>thee ſo;</hi> and whileſt <hi>ſo,</hi> cauſed <hi>thee</hi> to proſper, into <hi>that</hi> ſpirit which cauſed thee and <hi>honeſt men to ſuffer, againſt which thou waſt made ſo proſperous and ſuccesful?</hi> And being <hi>ſo,</hi> Canſt <hi>thou</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it otherwiſe to be with <hi>thee,</hi> then at <hi>this</hi> day it is, or look to proſper.</p>
               <p>Is not the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of the <hi>ſuffering</hi> people of <hi>God</hi> become a <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed</hi> thing? Is not the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of <hi>thoſe his</hi> people grown <hi>very</hi> cheap, and <hi>not</hi> laid to heart? Art not <hi>thou,</hi> inſtead of hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>loud</hi> cry of <hi>their</hi> Oppreſſions, and cloathing <hi>thy</hi> ſelfe with <hi>Zeal</hi> for their deliverance, become <hi>exceeding</hi> jealous of <hi>them,</hi> that <hi>they</hi> are deſigning againſt <hi>thee,</hi> and againſt <hi>thy</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom? Doth not this make <hi>thee</hi> to <hi>deal ſubtilly</hi> with them, to keep <hi>Bonds</hi> and <hi>Sufferings</hi> upon <hi>them,</hi> to ſtop <hi>thine</hi> ears at <hi>their</hi> ſufferings, and to permit <hi>thoſe violent, cruel</hi> and <hi>barbarous</hi> uſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of <hi>them,</hi> to go unpuniſhed, thereby (as <hi>thou</hi> thinkeſt) to keep <hi>them</hi> low, and under, and to depreſs <hi>their</hi> ſpirits, and by rendring <hi>them</hi> the <hi>prey</hi> and <hi>ſcorn</hi> of all, to ſecure <hi>thy</hi> ſelf of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29825:8"/> 
                  <hi>them,</hi> as to what <hi>thou</hi> feareſt <hi>they</hi> may attempt againſt <hi>thee?</hi> Hence cometh it not to paſs, that a <hi>bare</hi> ſuggeſtion of <hi>thoſe</hi> who <hi>thus evil</hi> entreat <hi>them,</hi> as that <hi>they are liſting of men;</hi> or that <hi>their meetings are great;</hi> or <hi>they are deſigning,</hi> with <hi>ſuch</hi> like, proves <hi>enough</hi> to turn <hi>thee</hi> from <hi>hearkening</hi> to the <hi>voice</hi> of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> which <hi>calls</hi> upon <hi>thee</hi> to puniſh ſuch <hi>evil</hi> doers, and to cauſe <hi>thee</hi> to liſten to the Enemy of <hi>thy</hi> ſoul, who ſeeks upon <hi>all</hi> occaſions to perſwade that <hi>thoſe</hi> are conſpiring againſt <hi>thee;</hi> who are ſo far from <hi>any ſuch</hi> thing, that <hi>they</hi> have not to <hi>thee</hi> ſo much as an <hi>ill</hi> thought, but in <hi>ſecret</hi> mourn and weep for <hi>thee,</hi> (know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the condition in which <hi>thou</hi> art) and are pained at the very heart, that <hi>thou</hi> mighteſt once hear and return from whence <hi>thou</hi> art fallen, that ſo the <hi>Indignation</hi> of the <hi>Lord, which is coming like a Whirlwind,</hi> may be turned away from <hi>thee,</hi> and ſo <hi>thou</hi> mayeſt come to enjoy the mercies for which <hi>thou</hi> haſt ſo long, and <hi>ſo</hi> ſorely travelled, <hi>the Eternal God is our witneſs that it is ſo,</hi> and <hi>our</hi> innocency herein ſhal be made <hi>clear as the light,</hi> and <hi>our upright dealing</hi> towards <hi>thee as the noon-day;</hi> and here do not <hi>they who watch for,</hi> and <hi>contrive,</hi> and <hi>act iniquity,</hi> eſcape and find encouragement from <hi>thee,</hi> and protection? And are not the <hi>innocent</hi> ſought to be cut off, for, againſt, and upon <hi>whom iniquity</hi> is <hi>watched, contrived</hi> and <hi>acted,</hi> as aforeſaid? And <hi>this</hi> manner of dealing found not the <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>God</hi> from the <hi>Spirit</hi> that <hi>is of this world,</hi> from the beginning? <hi>This Michaiah never propheſieth good of me, I hate him,</hi> ſaid <hi>that</hi> ſpirit in <hi>Ahab; Art thou he that troubleth Iſrael,</hi> ſaid <hi>he</hi> to <hi>Elijah? The Land is not able to bear all his words, for thus he ſaith, Jereboam ſhall dye by the Sword, and Iſrael ſhall ſurely be led away capture out of their own Land;</hi> ſent the <hi>High Prieſt</hi> at <hi>Bethel</hi> to <hi>King Jeroboam</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Amos,</hi> who ſpake <hi>theſe</hi> words from the <hi>mouth</hi> of the <hi>Lord, There is a certain People ſcattered abroad, and diſperſed amongſt the people in all the Provinces of the Kingdom, and their Laws are divers from all people, neither keep they the Kings Laws, therefore it is not for the Kings profit to ſuffer them; If it pleaſe the King, let it be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that they be deſtroyed &amp;c.</hi> Said <hi>Haman</hi> to <hi>Ahaſhuerus</hi> of the <hi>Jews. There are certain Jewes whom thou haſt ſet over the Affairs of the Province of Babylon; theſe men O King, have not regarded thee, they ſerve not thy Gods, nor worſhip the Golden Image which thou hast ſet up.</hi> Said <hi>certain Chaldeans which came near and accuſed the Jews
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29825:9"/> to Nebuchadnezzar That Daniel which is of the Children of the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity of Judah, regardeth not thee O King, nor the Decree which thou haſt ſigned, but maketh his Petition three times a day,</hi> ſaid <hi>the Preſidents of the Kingdom, the Governors and the Princes, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors and the Captains,</hi> concerning <hi>Daniel</hi> to King <hi>Darius. We have found this fellow perverting the Nation, and forbidding to give Tribute to Caeſar, ſaying that he himſelf is Chriſt a King,</hi> ſaid the <hi>Elders</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> and the <hi>chief Prieſts,</hi> and the <hi>Scribes,</hi> and the <hi>whole</hi> multitude of <hi>them</hi> in <hi>their</hi> accuſation of <hi>Jeſus</hi> unto <hi>Pilate. Thoſe who have turned the world up-ſide-down are come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo, whom Jaſon hath received, and thoſe all do contrary to the Decrees of Caeſar, ſaying that there is another King, one Jeſus,</hi> cryed the <hi>Jews who believed not, and were moved with envy, who tooke unto them certain lewd fellows of the baſer ſort, and gathered a company, and ſet all the City an Uproare, and aſſaulted the Houſe of Jaſon, &amp; drew him out, and certain Brethren, unto the Rulers of the City. W have found this man a peſtilent Fellow, and a mover of Sedition amone all the Jews throughout the world,</hi> ſaid <hi>Turtullus</hi> of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Foelix.</hi> This is what <hi>that</hi> ſpirit ſuggeſted throughout <hi>all</hi> Ages, on <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord</hi> in the <hi>Scriptures</hi> of <hi>Truth;</hi> and with <hi>this that</hi> ſpirit blinded the <hi>Kings, Princes</hi> and <hi>Rulers,</hi> and ſet <hi>them</hi> againſt the <hi>Lord,</hi> and againſt <hi>his annointed,</hi> which proved in the <hi>iſſue, their</hi> deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This is <hi>that</hi> the <hi>Biſhops</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Puritans,</hi> to the <hi>late King.</hi> This is <hi>that</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> brought <hi>forth</hi> the <hi>law</hi> in <hi>thoſe</hi> days againſt <hi>their</hi> Meetings <hi>to ſeek the Lord</hi> upon <hi>pretence</hi> of <hi>Conventicles;</hi> and with this the <hi>late</hi> King <hi>they blinded,</hi> and <hi>ſet him</hi> againſt <hi>theſe</hi> people, which became the overthrow of <hi>him, his Poſterity</hi> and <hi>followers,</hi> and of <hi>that</hi> generation, and of <hi>thoſe</hi> that joined with <hi>them.</hi> And <hi>this</hi> is <hi>that</hi> ſpirit <hi>that</hi> is now <hi>blinding</hi> of <hi>thee,</hi> who waſt the <hi>Lords Battel-Axe,</hi> and <hi>weapon</hi> of <hi>warre,</hi> to the <hi>cutting</hi> down of <hi>him,</hi> and <hi>thoſe</hi> whom after <hi>this</hi> manner <hi>it blinded,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſet</hi> againſt the <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>his</hi> people, and <hi>which</hi> is <hi>now</hi> ſetting of <hi>thee</hi> againſt the <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which in <hi>this</hi> fulneſs of the <hi>diſpenſation</hi> of <hi>times he</hi> is raiſing up to <hi>reign for ever and ever; Unto which ſpirit if thou continue to hearken, and to follow, and to be guided by, thou ſhalt be</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The <hi>11</hi> of the 5th Mon <hi>1656</hi> came this word of the Lord to me, and it was fulfilled the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. of the <hi>7.</hi> Mon. <hi>1658.</hi> the day on which he had his two great Victories at <hi>Dunbar</hi> and <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>cut off, the mouth of the Lord of Hoſts hath ſpoken it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore doth <hi>my</hi> heart mourn, &amp; <hi>my</hi> bowels are even tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned within me, leaſt <hi>thou</hi> ſhouldſt not <hi>know in this thy Day, the things that belong unto thy Peace,</hi> and <hi>ſo they be</hi> quite <hi>hid from thine
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29825:9"/> eyes;</hi> leaſt <hi>thou</hi> ſhouldſt not embrace the <hi>tender</hi> viſitation of the <hi>Lord,</hi> whoſe <hi>Arms</hi> are yet open to <hi>thee,</hi> and <hi>his</hi> long ſuffering, and patience, and love towards <hi>thee,</hi> calling <hi>thee</hi> to <hi>return</hi> and <hi>live,</hi> that <hi>thou</hi> mayeſt <hi>ſee the felicity of his choſen,</hi> and inſtead of ſetting againſt, <hi>come</hi> into <hi>that Kingdom,</hi> and be made a <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker</hi> of <hi>that glory</hi> which <hi>thou</hi> haſt been <hi>long looking,</hi> and <hi>ſighing,</hi> and <hi>travelling</hi> for, and which was in <hi>thine</hi> eye to be deſigned of <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>the end and iſſue of all the wars,</hi> though <hi>it thou</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not, but is <hi>now</hi> come and coming to be made manifeſt, and to be ſet up, of which <hi>there ſhall be no end,</hi> which <hi>thouſands</hi> of his Saints in <hi>this</hi> Nation are come to ſee and witneſs, which is not of <hi>this</hi> world, nor can be comprehended by the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of the <hi>Princes</hi> thereof, which it is come to cauſe to periſh, and to bring to nought; therefore it is that in <hi>this</hi> mighty day of <hi>his</hi> appearance, <hi>his Viſage is</hi> to <hi>them more marr'd then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mans; in him they ſee no comelineſs nor beauty whereby they ſhould deſire him;</hi> therefore it is that <hi>with one conſent they are confederate; all Forms</hi> and <hi>Profeſſions, Judgements</hi> and <hi>Opinions</hi> without the life, with the <hi>more</hi> groſs and <hi>rude,</hi> and <hi>vile</hi> people of the world, and drawn together, and <hi>muſter'd</hi> unto Battel in, by, &amp; under <hi>that</hi> ſpirit, where <hi>they</hi> are <hi>one,</hi> and which is <hi>one</hi> in <hi>them all,</hi> as the <hi>Day</hi> doth <hi>now</hi> manifeſt, and their <hi>fruits</hi> do make to appear, <hi>with a rage reaching up to heauen,</hi> againſt the <hi>Lamb</hi> and <hi>his followers,</hi> who is <hi>lowly</hi> and <hi>meek; not reſiſting evil,</hi> nor <hi>lifting up its voice in the ſtreet becauſe of violence and oppreſſion,</hi> nor <hi>ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deliverance,</hi> but laying <hi>down its body as the ground, and as the ſtreet to them that go over, who have ſaid, Bow down, that we may go over,</hi> who <hi>haue no kindred upon Earth,</hi> nor <hi>none to enquire after their blood,</hi> or that <hi>pleadeth their cauſe,</hi> or that is <hi>their helper and deliverer</hi> amongſt the <hi>men</hi> thereof, in <hi>this</hi> hour of <hi>its</hi> ſufferings, wherein <hi>its teſtimony is finiſhing,</hi> and the <hi>meaſure of Iniquity fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling up.</hi> Nevertheleſs, <hi>Conquering, and to conquer he rides on, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Armies of Heaven following him; and through the blood of his Croſs,</hi> through <hi>ſufferings overcoming;</hi> and <hi>yet</hi> a <hi>little</hi> while, and <hi>to him whom man deſpiſeth, to him whom the Nation abhorreth, to a ſervant of Rulers, Kings ſhall ſee and ariſe, Princes alſo ſhall worſhip; for the time is come, and coming, wherein the Lords Plant of Renown ſhall be exalted, unto whom every knee ſhall bow, and every Tongue confeſs; and the Nation and Kingdom that will not ſerve it, ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29825:10"/> yea, thoſe Nations ſhall be utterly waſted; every Battel of the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier is with confuſed noiſe, and Garments rolled in Blood; but this ſhall be with burning and fewel of Fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is <hi>he</hi> in whom <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Noah,</hi> and the <hi>Fathers</hi> belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, with whom <hi>Enoch walked,</hi> and <hi>was tranſlated;</hi> whoſe <hi>Day Abraham ſaw,</hi> and <hi>rejoiced;</hi> of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi> ſpake that <hi>he ſhould come;</hi> this is <hi>He</hi> who was <hi>in the Church in the Wilderneſs; with the Angel that ſpake to him in Mount Sinai; and with the Fathers who received the lively Oracles:</hi> This is <hi>He</hi> who <hi>was manifested in time;</hi> the <hi>holy Thing that was born of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin;</hi> who <hi>by the eternal Spirit offered up himſelf once for all; and by one offering perfected for ever thoſe that are ſanctified.</hi> This is <hi>He</hi> whom the <hi>Apoſtles witneſſed</hi> to be <hi>riſen</hi> and <hi>aſcended far above all Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipallities and Powers, and every Name this is named both in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, that he might fill all things; who is the Head of his Church; the fulneſs of him who filleth all in all; the Myſterie hid from ages and generations, Christ in us the hope of glory: The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king known of which is the Riches of the Glory to the Gentiles:</hi> This is <hi>He</hi> that was with <hi>thee</hi> in <hi>thy</hi> ſtreights, <hi>thy</hi> ſtrength, <hi>thy</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor, <hi>thy</hi> Deliverer; to whom <hi>thou</hi> didſt <hi>promiſe,</hi> to whom <hi>thou</hi> didſt <hi>vow,</hi> and who requireth <hi>thee now</hi> to <hi>perform;</hi> this is <hi>He,</hi> a <hi>meaſure</hi> from <hi>whom thou</hi> haſt, which hath <hi>ſhewn thee evil,</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved</hi> and <hi>judged thee</hi> for <hi>ſin,</hi> and <hi>cauſed thee</hi> to <hi>breath after God;</hi> and <hi>after Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>after Righteouſneſs,</hi> which <hi>ſometimes</hi> did <hi>refreſh thee,</hi> and <hi>warmed thine heart, ſtrengthened thee,</hi> and gave <hi>thee many</hi> and <hi>large</hi> openings: This is <hi>He, the making way for the ſetting up of whoſe Kingdom was the deſign and end of the Lord in the Wars:</hi> This is <hi>He</hi> who <hi>was to come,</hi> ſo <hi>earneſtly looked for, who is come the ſecond time without ſin unto ſalvation;</hi> and <hi>whom to be come, Thouſands</hi> of <hi>his Saints</hi> do witneſs; <hi>Eternal living prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be unto him who hath loved us, and viſited us with the Day-ſpring from on high, and waſhed away our ſins in his Blood.</hi> This is <hi>he</hi> that calleth <hi>thee</hi> to lay down <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Scepter at <hi>his</hi> feet, whoſe <hi>Scepter is a Scepter of Righteouſneſſe;</hi> by <hi>it</hi> to be <hi>guided</hi> and <hi>acted,</hi> that ſo <hi>thine</hi> Enemies may be confounded, and <hi>thine</hi> Houſe eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed. This is <hi>He</hi> who <hi>is the Heir of all things, by whom the worlds were made; the brightneſs of his Fathers glory, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Image of his Perſon; the upholder of all things by the Word of his Power; the Light of the World; the Covenant of Light to the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29825:10"/> Gentiles; the Life of Men; the true Light, that lighteth every one that cometh into the world;</hi> who is <hi>come into the world, but the world</hi> knows <hi>him not;</hi> who hath <hi>ſuffered,</hi> and <hi>ſtill ſuffers</hi> at <hi>thy</hi> hands, and by the <hi>people</hi> under <hi>thy</hi> Government; who preſerved <hi>thee</hi> when <hi>thou</hi> waſt a <hi>ſufferer,</hi> and exalted <hi>thee</hi> when <hi>thou</hi> waſt <hi>little</hi> in <hi>thine</hi> own eyes, <hi>despiſed</hi> and <hi>contemned;</hi> and when <hi>thou</hi> didſt plead the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>his innocent people,</hi> who <hi>ſuffered</hi> without <hi>cauſe; who</hi> becauſe <hi>thou</hi> haſt hardened <hi>thy</hi> heart, and turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>him,</hi> hath turned from <hi>thee his</hi> preſence, <hi>Wiſdom</hi> from <hi>thy Counſels, Spirit</hi> from <hi>thy Men</hi> of <hi>War,</hi> and <hi>Succeſs</hi> from <hi>thine undertakings,</hi> and is <hi>stripping</hi> of <hi>thee</hi> of <hi>thy Fence</hi> &amp; <hi>Guard,</hi> and making <hi>thee naked</hi> and <hi>bare,</hi> and is <hi>coming againſt thee;</hi> therefore <hi>prepare to meet him</hi> whileſt <hi>he is in the way,</hi> who ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>thee</hi> where <hi>thou</hi> haſt been, and where <hi>thou</hi> art; and what <hi>thou</hi> haſt done, and what <hi>thou</hi> art doing, and the way to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, which is yet open. <hi>His tender Viſitation of Love this is to thee,</hi> who hath <hi>long waited to be gracious,</hi> and <hi>born</hi> and <hi>ſuffered</hi> thorough <hi>him</hi> who is a <hi>lover</hi> of <hi>thy</hi> ſoul, known unto <hi>thee</hi> by the Name of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>GEORGE BISHOPE.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Briſtol,</hi> 
                     <date>the 16. of the 5. Mon. 1656.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To <hi>RICHARD,</hi> Protector of theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>Theſe Preſent.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>R. Protector,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>SEeing</hi> thy <hi>Father is fallen aſleep, and</hi> thou his <hi>Son art ſet upon the</hi> Throne <hi>of the</hi> Government <hi>of</hi> theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> I <hi>am</hi> moved <hi>of the</hi> Lord <hi>to counſel</hi> thee, To heed him by whom Kings reign, and Princes decree Justice, the Principle of God in thee, which moves to Juſtice, and to Mercy, and the fear of the Lord; and diſcovers and judges the contrary; which if thou doeſt, and giveſt up to be governed by it, the Lord will daſh in pieces all the conſultations againſt thee and thy Fathers houſe, and will ſettle the Throne under thee, and make thee a dread and a terror to all the Nations round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29825:11"/> as he made thy Father: But if thou ſhalt refuſe to hearken un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and to be guided by it, the Lord will<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>This</hi> was <hi>fulfilled</hi> the <hi>later</hi> end of the <hi>Month</hi> called <hi>April,</hi> and the <hi>beginning</hi> of the <hi>Month</hi> called <hi>May,</hi> following, when the <hi>Army</hi> cauſed <hi>him</hi> to <hi>diſsolve</hi> his Parliament, and the <hi>ſeſsion</hi> of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> ſucceeding, to <hi>reſign bis</hi> Protector<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; as was <hi>alſo fulfilled,</hi> what <hi>I</hi> had ſeen in the <hi>Eternal,</hi> in the <hi>Month</hi> called <hi>June</hi> preceding, as <hi>I</hi> was walking in the <hi>great</hi> Court in <hi>White-hall,</hi> and weighing <hi>in that which is not of this World,</hi> O. Protector, <hi>his</hi> Council, (which was then ſitting) <hi>his</hi> Family and Government, viz. <hi>The earth riſing, and as it were, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the right hand, and the left, and overturning him and his Government, his Council, and Family</hi>— VVith <hi>which,</hi> as ſoon as <hi>I</hi> came out of <hi>White-hall</hi> Gate, I acquainted a <hi>Friend</hi> of <hi>mine</hi> whom <hi>I</hi> met by the <hi>Banqueting</hi>-houſe, and which <hi>I</hi> again ſaw as <hi>I</hi> was <hi>on my</hi> way to <hi>Briſtol,</hi> a mile or two out of <hi>London,</hi> as <hi>I</hi> was turn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d about by the <hi>moving</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and the <hi>direction</hi> of <hi>his</hi> ſpirit, ſitting on <hi>my</hi> Horſe, and looking on VVhite-hall By which <hi>doubling</hi> of the <hi>Viſion, I</hi> knew that <hi>it</hi> ſhould (as it qu ckly hath) aſſuredly come to paſs.</note> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturn thee; <hi>for</hi> he <hi>hath</hi> overturned, over-turned, overturned, <hi>that</hi> he <hi>may</hi> reign whoſe right it is, <hi>and</hi> he is come to reigne whoſe right it is, of the encreaſe of whoſe government and peace there ſhall be no end; upon the Throne of David, and upon his Kingdom, to order it, and to eſtabliſh it with Judgement and Justice, henceforth, even for ever. <hi>Thus in</hi> bowels <hi>of</hi> love <hi>&amp;</hi> tenderneſs, <hi>in</hi> obedience <hi>to the</hi> Lord, <hi>as</hi> I <hi>am</hi> moved <hi>of</hi> him, <hi>that it may be well with</hi> thee <hi>and</hi> thy <hi>Poſterity after</hi> thee, <hi>have</hi> I <hi>written, who am known to</hi> thee <hi>by the name of</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>GEO. BISHOPE.</signed>
                  <dateline>Briſtol <date>
                        <hi>9. of the 7. Mo. 1658.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To the <hi>General Council</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> in whom is riſen the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>Good old Cauſe,</hi> theſe following Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars are tender'd, in order to the carrying thorough of what is by <hi>them</hi> begun, for the <hi>good</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> and <hi>all honeſt</hi> men in it. <hi>By</hi> a <hi>Friend,</hi> who though <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote</hi> in <hi>perſon,</hi> yet <hi>wiſhes well</hi> to the <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>them,</hi> and to <hi>both</hi> on <hi>that</hi> foot, <hi>thus</hi> contributes, Viz.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>HEed</hi> the <hi>Principle</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> in <hi>you</hi> all, which ſhews <hi>your</hi> goings aſtray; and reform what <hi>it</hi> ſhews <hi>you</hi> to be amiſs in <hi>your</hi> ſelves, as to <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Purge</hi> the <hi>Army</hi> of <hi>every</hi> Branch that <hi>ſprings</hi> not from the <hi>Root</hi> of the <hi>Good old Cauſe;</hi> and ſee that the <hi>degenerate</hi> plant be pluckt up.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:29825:11"/>3. <hi>Call</hi> back <hi>every honeſt</hi> man that was <hi>caſhiered</hi> for the <hi>Cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Make ſome</hi> of <hi>Parliament, Court, Council, Army, examples,</hi> who acted in the <hi>late hateful</hi> degeneration, and would have <hi>betrayed</hi> and <hi>deſtroyed you</hi> and the <hi>Cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Read</hi> over, <hi>conſider,</hi> and <hi>ſtand</hi> to <hi>your Virgin</hi> Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and <hi>do your firſt works.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Declare</hi> in what <hi>ye</hi> underſtand the <hi>good old Cauſe</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, and <hi>your</hi> reſolutions to <hi>adhere</hi> thereunto, and <hi>never</hi> again to <hi>deviate</hi> therefrom.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Entruſt ſuch every</hi> where with <hi>places</hi> of <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</hi> in whom doth <hi>live,</hi> and <hi>is</hi> the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>Cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Summon</hi> the <hi>ſurviving</hi> Members of the <hi>famous</hi> Long Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (who managed and carryed thorough the <hi>Good old Cauſe</hi>) and <hi>Council of State, in Statu quo.</hi> Declare that the <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> is removed: That the <hi>People</hi> obey <hi>them,</hi> as before <hi>that</hi> obſtruction, to <hi>all</hi> intents and purpoſes. And a <hi>General</hi> Indempnity of <hi>all</hi> that hath been done, whether in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>that</hi> obſtruction, or purſuance of the <hi>ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Protect</hi> the <hi>(now) Protector,</hi> and let <hi>him</hi> enjoy <hi>his</hi> Perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and Paternal Eſtate.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Vex the Midianites, (i.e.</hi> the <hi>Lawyers</hi>) and <hi>ſmite them, for they vex you with their wiles wherewith they have beguiled you in the matter of</hi> Peer <hi>and Cosby,</hi> (i.e. <hi>the King and Protector.</hi>) <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form</hi> the <hi>Laws,</hi> and the <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> of <hi>them;</hi> and <hi>ſeverely</hi> puniſh the <hi>perverters</hi> of the <hi>Righteouſneſs of each.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Remember Amalek</hi> (i.e. the <hi>ſoul-murthering,</hi> and <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence-binding Clrgy-man and what he did unto you by the way when ye were come out of Aegypt, how he met you by the way, and ſmote the hindmoſt of you, even all that were feeble behind you, when ye were faint and weary, and he feared not God.</hi> Therefore <hi>blot out the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of Amalek from under heaven, (i.e.</hi> the <hi>principle</hi> that is againſt <hi>Liberty of Conſcience) ye ſhall not forget it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12: <hi>Set</hi> at <hi>liberty forthwith all</hi> the <hi>Conſciencious</hi> People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> now in <hi>Bonds</hi> becauſe of <hi>their</hi> conſcience to <hi>God,</hi> (the <hi>good old Cauſe</hi>) on <hi>whoſe</hi> ſufferings preſented the <hi>late</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the <hi>ſaid</hi> Parliament inſtead of enquiring into the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> ſet <hi>their</hi> foot (as <hi>they</hi> had done a <hi>little before</hi>) on the <hi>good
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29825:12"/> old Cauſe,</hi> viz. <hi>In aſſerting a coercive Power in Religion, Worſhip, &amp;c.</hi> and would have done on <hi>you once for all,</hi> and have deſtroyed <hi>You All;</hi> yea after <hi>all your</hi> Conqueſts of <hi>them all,</hi> had not the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>Good Old Cauſe</hi> lifted up <hi>your</hi> foot upon <hi>them All.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <date>
                     <hi>April</hi> 27. 1659.</date>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Copy of another <hi>LETTER</hi> ſent ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after to the ſaid <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Officers.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Friends,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SEeing the <hi>Lord</hi> hath heard <hi>you</hi> in <hi>your</hi> diſtreſs, and the voice of <hi>your</hi> Cry hath entred into <hi>his</hi> ears, when <hi>yee</hi> were near ſwallowing up by <hi>your</hi> proud Enemy, and hath delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>you</hi> when there was <hi>ſcarce a ſtep betwixt you, and the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of you</hi> and <hi>your friends,</hi> and <hi>the Publick Cauſe of theſe Nations,</hi> and hath ſpared and given you <hi>(once more) ſpace and time</hi> to <hi>recover ſtrength,</hi> and <hi>your</hi> dying reputation amongſt <hi>honeſt</hi> men, <hi>before yee go hence, and be no more.</hi> It lies upon <hi>me</hi> (as a <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time</hi> fellow-labourer with <hi>you</hi> in the <hi>work</hi> of the <hi>Nation;</hi> yea, as <hi>moved of the Lord</hi>) to warn <hi>you,</hi> That <hi>yee bring forth fruits meet for repentance;</hi> for, verily <hi>friends,</hi> it is <hi>your</hi> day of trial from the <hi>Lord,</hi> wherein <hi>He</hi> is trying <hi>you,</hi> proving <hi>you,</hi> to ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be <hi>ſuch</hi> an <hi>heart</hi> in <hi>you,</hi> to do according to <hi>all yee</hi> have ſaid in <hi>your</hi> late<note place="margin">
                     <hi>April</hi> 6. 1659.</note> Repreſentation <hi>(even that yee would fear him, and keepe all his Commandments alwayes, that it may be well with you and your children for ever.)</hi> And for <hi>this</hi> purpoſe <hi>he</hi> hath <hi>(once more)</hi> overthrown <hi>your</hi> Enemies, and <hi>in the thing wherein they dealt proudly, hath</hi> ſhewn <hi>himſelf above them,</hi> and put the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>theſe</hi> Nations into <hi>your</hi> hands, to try <hi>You,</hi> and prove <hi>You,</hi> and to ſee whether <hi>ye</hi> will do as <hi>ye</hi> ſpeak. If therefore <hi>the Good old Cauſe againſt Tyranny and intollerable Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, in matters Civil and Religious,</hi> (as <hi>ye</hi> expreſt <hi>it</hi> in <hi>your</hi> ſaid Repreſentation) <hi>whereupon ye firſt engaged, and unto which the Lord hath in ſuch a continual Series of Providence given ſo ſignal a Teſtimony; and for the carrying on whereof, there hath been ſuch a plentiful pouring forth of Treaſure, Prayers, Tears and Blood, during
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29825:12"/> the late War; (in the difficulties and dangers whereof, ye alſo (the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Monuments</hi> (as <hi>ye</hi> ſay; and truly <hi>ye</hi> are ſo, and 'tis good for <hi>you</hi> ever to mind <hi>it) of Patience &amp; Mercy (have had your ſhares) be not throughly aſſerted &amp; vindicated.</hi> If in <hi>very</hi> deed &amp; <hi>good</hi> earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>ye appear not now as ever, equally endeared to the Good old Cauſe, and utter Enemies to all Tyranny, Oppreſſion, and diſturbance; of the publike Peace, under what pretences ſoever. If whileſt your Lives and preſent Capacities are continued to you, ye pluck not the wicked out of their Places whereſoever they may be diſcovered, either among your ſelves, or in any other Places of Truſt. If Law and Manners ſo frequently declared for, and ſo earneſtly expected by all ſober unbyaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed men, be not reformed. If the Courſe of Juſtice and Bowels of Mercy be not opened. If the wayes of holineſs he not encouraged. If a ſtop be not put to the inundation of Malignancie and Prophaneneſs: If there be not ſuch a publike aſſerting of the Good Old Cauſe, and a Iuſtification and confirmation of all proceedings in proſecution and maintenance thereof, and Declaration againſt its Enemies, as may (for the future) deter all perſons from ſpeaking or attempting any thing to the prejudice thereof, and of the Perſons that have acted in the proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of it, and afford preſent Security to the Civil and Religious Right and Liberties of theſe Nations, and the Peace thereof.</hi> It <hi>the Liberty of good and well affected People in repairing with freedom to their Meetings for the Worſhip of God (of late much violated by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting and imprſoning</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Yea, cruel whipping.</note> 
                  <hi>their</hi> Perſons) <hi>be not ſtill aſſerted.</hi> If <hi>wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſoever ye have back ſudden, ye do not take ſhame to your ſelves,</hi> as (in <hi>your</hi> ſaid Repreſentation <hi>ye</hi> confeſs) <hi>ye have Cauſe;</hi> and ſay, you <hi>deſire to take frame</hi> and further, that <hi>ye cannot but bewail your own great failings and turning aſide:</hi> And if (by the <hi>doing</hi> of <hi>theſe</hi> things) <hi>ye do no receive the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>earts of your faithful friends, and vindicate your own integrity againſt all cenſures and jealouſies, &amp; make it to appear, that ye did indeed engage in judgment and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for the juſt rights and liberties civil and religious, of your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and not as a mercenary Army,</hi> as in <hi>your,</hi> ſaid Repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>yee</hi> ſay and affirm (and as hath been before rehearſed) <hi>yee have as members of the Army, often ſolemnly declared, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out appeals to God</hi> ſay <hi>ye) for your ſincerity therein.</hi> If <hi>from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth the people of the Lord ſhall ſuffer, or be continued in their ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, becauſe of their conſcience to God</hi> (the <hi>Good-old-Cauſe</hi>). <hi>Hear O heavens, and give ear O earth,</hi> and be <hi>yee</hi> witneſſes, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29825:13"/> 
                  <hi>all</hi> good men; <hi>ye ſhall not</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>All</hi> are <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſses</hi> of the <hi>fulfilling</hi> of this.</note> 
                  <hi>proſper, the Lord hath ſpoken it.</hi> Therefore <hi>up</hi> and <hi>be doing; fear not, nor be diſmayed, the preſence of the Lord will be with you in theſe things (as heretofore) and his arme ſtretched out for you (as in former daies) againſt your Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries.</hi> That which <hi>touched</hi> and <hi>awakened</hi> the <hi>honeſty</hi> in <hi>you,</hi> and brought <hi>you</hi> into <hi>ſenſibleneſs,</hi> and to <hi>confeſs,</hi> and to <hi>act</hi> hitherto (viz. <hi>the grace of God, the light of Chriſt in you</hi>) will carry <hi>you</hi> through, <hi>yee</hi> abiding and believing therein. This is <hi>your</hi> day, a day <hi>yee</hi> thought not of, nor could <hi>ſcarce</hi> hope for; viz. <hi>to have the publick Intereſt ſaved utterly from ſinking, during the late deſperate wrecks</hi> and <hi>daſhings on the rocks, and your ſelvs in it deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered into a capacity to ſave and ſecure it, and your own particulars, who were firſt deſigned to be ſunk.</hi> If a <hi>man</hi> ſhould have told <hi>you</hi> this, <hi>ye</hi> could not have believed <hi>it.</hi> This is <hi>your</hi> hour of <hi>tryal,</hi> wherein, as <hi>I</hi> ſaid, <hi>the Lord is trying you,</hi> to ſee whether, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing delivered, and having power in <hi>your</hi> hands, <hi>ye</hi> will ſtand by, and ſecure <hi>your</hi> ſelves and <hi>it.</hi> Nothing <hi>(now)</hi> but <hi>integri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty, uprightneſs</hi> of <hi>heart, truth in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts,</hi> and <hi>proportionable</hi> actings wil ſerve <hi>If ye</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Notwithſtanding</hi> this cloſe <hi>and</hi> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory <hi>VVarning from the</hi> Lord <hi>ſo</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced <hi>and</hi> obreſted, <hi>yet</hi> May <hi>(ſo called) the</hi> 12. <hi>following, being the eighth day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the</hi> date <hi>of</hi> this <hi>warning, and the</hi> 20. <hi>after</hi> their <hi>Deliverance, and the</hi> 36 <hi>after the</hi> Date <hi>of</hi> their <hi>ſaid Repreſentation; in which</hi> they ſo much complained, <hi>and</hi> confeſsed, <hi>and</hi> bewailed, <hi>and</hi> Reſolved, <hi>and</hi> Declared <hi>to the</hi> contrary <hi>(as hath be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n ſaid)</hi> They ſtarted aſide point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blanck, <hi>in</hi> changing <hi>the</hi> Cauſe <hi>of</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty <hi>of</hi> Conſcience <hi>in the</hi> 6th. <hi>Article of</hi> their <hi>Addreſs, which by</hi> ſome <hi>of</hi> them <hi>was</hi> that <hi>Day, viz.</hi> May 12. <hi>Preſented to the</hi> Parliament, <hi>and the</hi> 27. of the 10th. <hi>Month following, (called December)</hi> they were gone; thoſe <hi>men whom they</hi> ſhut <hi>our,</hi> flowing <hi>over</hi> their <hi>Heads, (whileſt the</hi> Officers lay <hi>under) that</hi> day <hi>into the</hi> Parliament, <hi>by the hand of</hi> thoſe <hi>very Souldiers who were chiefly</hi> inſtrumental <hi>in the</hi> keeping <hi>them out, and had declared for the Officers, which is remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable; but that which makes it the</hi> more <hi>obſervable, is, That the</hi> Hand <hi>is fallen</hi> Firſt <hi>on</hi> thoſe <hi>very Officers that</hi> preſented <hi>the</hi> ſaid <hi>Addreſs, who were looked upon, and were in</hi> their <hi>day, the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt among them for Conſcience</hi> Liberty. <hi>Here's ſtarting aſide, and a</hi> Farewel <hi>indeed; the</hi> Lord is righteous, <hi>let men</hi> tremble before him.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtart aſide again, farewell; ye</hi> have confeſt againſt <hi>your</hi> ſelves, and <hi>your</hi> Repreſentation is witneſs againſt <hi>you; Deliverance ſhall come another way, but ye and your Houſe ſhall periſh. A war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from the Lord God it is unto you all,</hi> by and through <hi>him</hi> who is,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your <hi>friend,</hi> and <hi>tenderly</hi> deſires it may be <hi>well</hi> with <hi>you,</hi> both <hi>now,</hi> and <hi>for ever. GEO. BISHOPE.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Briſtol</hi> 
                     <date>the 4. of 3. Mo. 1659.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:29825:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To the</hi> Supreme Authority <hi>of</hi> theſe <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the</hi> PARLIAMENT <hi>of the</hi> Common-wealth <hi>of</hi> England, <hi>am</hi> I moved of the LORD to write.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Friends,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THis <hi>Day</hi> to have ſeen, was <hi>lately beyond</hi> the <hi>thoughts,</hi> of <hi>any,</hi> He that ſhould have told <hi>you</hi> but a <hi>very</hi> few daies <hi>before</hi> the <hi>late</hi> Parlaments diſſolution, that the <hi>Power</hi> which was <hi>ſo near</hi> the ſwallowing up of <hi>all,</hi> ſhould be <hi>ſo ſoon</hi> ſcattered: That <hi>thoſe</hi> who were made <hi>inſtrumental</hi> (through a <hi>wrong</hi> pilotage) to waſte <hi>this</hi> Common-wealth on <hi>ſuch</hi> deſperate Rocks, <hi>during</hi> theſe <hi>laſt</hi> ſix years (the interval of <hi>your</hi> ſteerage) ſhould bee awakened to ſee <hi>their</hi> danger, and to <hi>ſet</hi> (yea <hi>pray you</hi>) to the <hi>Helm</hi> again; that <hi>they</hi> and <hi>you</hi> together, ſhould be put into <hi>ſuch</hi> a capacity (the <hi>like</hi> was <hi>never</hi>) to <hi>aſſert</hi> and <hi>ſettle</hi> the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> (preſerved <hi>in</hi> and <hi>after</hi> all) and to <hi>ſecure it themſelves</hi> and <hi>you.</hi> That the <hi>hopes</hi> of <hi>Englands</hi> enemies ſhould ſo <hi>ſuddenly</hi> be <hi>daſht,</hi> when at the <hi>higheſt</hi> pitch and confidence to have prevailed againſt <hi>it,</hi> and <hi>their</hi> deſigns ſtruck <hi>backwards,</hi> who were ready to cry <hi>Aha! ſhe is broken, which was the Gates of the people, ſhe is turned unto us; we ſhall be repleniſhed, when ſhe is laid waſte: ſhee is given us to conſume (when as the Lord was there) this is the day we have looked for.</hi> That <hi>your</hi> friends who (ſeeing <hi>ſuch</hi> things) for <hi>very anguiſh</hi> and <hi>vexation</hi> of <hi>ſpirit,</hi> were even <hi>giving up the ghoſt,</hi> ſhould be (as it were in the <hi>twinkling of an eye) revived</hi> and brought <hi>back again</hi> from the <hi>gates</hi> of the <hi>grave, I</hi> ſay, <hi>He</hi> that ſhould have told <hi>you,</hi> but a <hi>little while ſince,</hi> that <hi>ſo</hi> it ſhould be, <hi>could ye have believed it?</hi> Would <hi>yee</hi> not have ſaid, <hi>he</hi> dreamed? Or, are <hi>ye</hi> not <hi>like them that dream? now that the Lord hath</hi> (thus) <hi>turned back the captivity of the Common-wealth;</hi> yea, whilſt <hi>yee</hi> are told of <hi>it,</hi> whilſt <hi>your</hi> eies are ſeeing, and <hi>your</hi> hands exerciſed in the work <hi>thereof.</hi> What <hi>man</hi> could have ſeen <hi>this day</hi> through the <hi>late thick</hi> clouds, what <hi>arme</hi> could have brought about <hi>ſuch</hi> an <hi>act?</hi> What <hi>Counſel</hi> have deſigned it? But <hi>this</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> hath done,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29825:14"/> that <hi>he may bring to paſs His Act, His ſtrange Act. This</hi> wonder hath <hi>he</hi> wrought (beyond all <hi>his mighty</hi> works of wonder done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>your</hi> eies) that it may appear that <hi>his own arm hath brought ſalvation,</hi> and <hi>that his fury hath upheld him, when he looked, and there was none to help, and wondred that there was none to uphold Theſe</hi> are <hi>his</hi> doings, who <hi>is come to reward every man according to his works:</hi> And <hi>thus</hi> it becom'd <hi>him</hi> to do, who is <hi>come from Edom with dyed Garments, from Bozrah glorious in his Apparel, travelling in the Greatneſs of his Strength, who ſpeaks in Righteouſneſs, mighty to ſave.</hi> And wherefore hath <hi>he</hi> done it? Friends, let <hi>me</hi> deal <hi>plainly</hi> with <hi>you,</hi> and ſuffer <hi>me</hi> a little whileſt <hi>I</hi> am ſpeaking to <hi>you</hi> from <hi>God. Ye were wronged, ye were ſlandered, ye were abuſed, ye were caſt out (and the Commonwealth with you) as abominable; you (and what the Lord had done for, and by you, were made the ſcorn and the deriſion of the Nations, whom his dread on you had made to tremble, (I have ſeen it, ſaith the Lord, and am witneſs) and he is come (who is a God of Faithfulneſs and Truth, the Judge of the whole Earth, who will Judge the World with Righteouſneſs, and the People Earth, who will Judge the World with Righteouſneſs, and the People with Equity) to do you Right, and this Right hath he done you (in a wonder) before the face of all People, and proportioned your healing to your wound; yea your reparation hath he cauſed to exceed your Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; Friends, fear not, for God is with you.</hi> And this <hi>He</hi> hath done that <hi>He may try you, and prove you,</hi> and ſee whether <hi>ye</hi> will do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>all</hi> that <hi>ye</hi> have <hi>ſaid</hi> and <hi>declared;</hi> according to <hi>all</hi> that the <hi>Nation</hi> hath <hi>bled</hi> for, and <hi>ſuffered;</hi> according to <hi>all ye</hi> have <hi>vow'd</hi> and <hi>promiſed</hi> to <hi>God</hi> in <hi>ſecret,</hi> in the day of <hi>your</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, if ever <hi>he</hi> ſhould give <hi>Power again</hi> into <hi>your</hi> hands: Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>all</hi> that <hi>ye</hi> ought to do, and to what is the <hi>end</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> in <hi>this his late wonderful</hi> and <hi>aſtoniſhing diſpenſation:</hi> And <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily (Friends) this</hi> is <hi>your Day</hi> of <hi>Tryal</hi> from the <hi>Lord,</hi> wherein <hi>he</hi> hath given <hi>you</hi> the <hi>Day ye</hi> deſired, (a <hi>full</hi> opportunity, the <hi>fulleſt</hi> that was <hi>ever: Look not for ſuch another</hi>) to do as <hi>ye</hi> have ſaid, and to perform what <hi>he</hi> requireth of <hi>you,</hi> and with <hi>you</hi> he will be <hi>(therein)</hi> as <hi>heretofore,</hi> and <hi>greater</hi> things <hi>ye</hi> ſhall do, <hi>ye abiding with him. Moved</hi> of the <hi>Lord God Almighty I</hi> am, to tell <hi>you</hi> ſo, who hath given <hi>all Nations, Kingdoms,</hi> and <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> a <hi>Day,</hi> and to <hi>thoſe</hi> who have gone <hi>before you,</hi> a <hi>Day;</hi> and to <hi>him</hi> that came <hi>after you,</hi> a <hi>Day;</hi> and <hi>this</hi> is <hi>your Day;</hi> therefore <hi>in this your Day, know the things that belong un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29825:14"/> your peace:</hi> Be <hi>liberal</hi> to <hi>God</hi> in <hi>ſuffering no</hi> man to <hi>ſuffer</hi> for <hi>his</hi> Conſcience, as <hi>he</hi> hath been <hi>liberal</hi> to <hi>you</hi> in <hi>ſuffering</hi> none to injure <hi>you</hi> and go unpuniſhed, what ever were <hi>their</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Be <hi>liberal</hi> to the <hi>Nation</hi> in giving <hi>it its</hi> Right, as <hi>it</hi> hath been <hi>liberal</hi> unto <hi>you,</hi> in hazarding <hi>its all</hi> in <hi>your</hi> ſervice for the recovery of <hi>its</hi> Rights. <hi>Repeal</hi> the <hi>Laws</hi> againſt <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and the <hi>Liberties</hi> of the <hi>Nation;</hi> and make <hi>no</hi> Laws but <hi>what</hi> may anſwer <hi>that</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and the <hi>Nations</hi> Liberties. <hi>Reform</hi> the <hi>Laws,</hi> and the <hi>evil</hi> adminiſtration of <hi>them. Check</hi> the <hi>Licentiouſneſs</hi> of the <hi>Clergy. Take</hi> away the <hi>cruel</hi> oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Tythes,</hi> and <hi>compulſive Maintenance;</hi> and <hi>let them who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be Goſpel-Miniſters, be content with Goſpel-Maintenance. Join</hi> not with <hi>them,</hi> nor <hi>conſult,</hi> whom <hi>God hath curst,</hi> (whether <hi>Ministers</hi> (ſo called) or <hi>People,</hi> or <hi>both</hi> joined together) nor <hi>fear them, leaſt God</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">How this hath been ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt.</note> 
                  <hi>confound you before them. Make no</hi> Laws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Truth</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Conſcience. Come</hi> into a <hi>ſenſible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> (in <hi>common</hi>) of the <hi>ſufferings</hi> and <hi>welfare</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> ſo as the <hi>People</hi> by <hi>your</hi> tenderneſs, may feel <hi>you</hi> touch't with the <hi>ſence</hi> of <hi>their</hi> ſufferings. <hi>Be not lifted up,</hi> becauſe <hi>God</hi> hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>your</hi> Cauſe, and executed Judgement for <hi>you;</hi> but be <hi>ye</hi> therefore laid low, to execute Judgement for <hi>God,</hi> and to plead the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>his</hi> People. <hi>Think not your Mountain ſo ſtrong that ye ſhall never be moved, but rather be in expectation</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">It was but the <hi>12th.</hi> of the <hi>Month</hi> called <hi>October</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, and the door was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain <hi>ſhut</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>them.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>every day, (not knowing what ſhall be to morrow) that it may be moved and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, becauſe it may be moved to give a good account to God and man when it ſhall be moved. Take heed</hi> of taking liberty to do and ſpeak as <hi>ye</hi> pleaſe, becauſe <hi>ye are Judges of the Law;</hi> but <hi>ſo ſpeak,</hi> and <hi>ſo do,</hi> as <hi>thoſe who ſhall be judged by the Law of Liberty.</hi> Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Let</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>VVhat a</hi> tender Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>was this of the</hi> Lords love? <hi>and how will</hi> it <hi>leave</hi> them without excuſe in the day that is at hand, (<hi>yea that already is</hi> begun <hi>upon</hi> them) wherein he that ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the heart, and tryeth the Reins, will ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to every man according to his work, <hi>as in the</hi> end of this <hi>Letter I have ſpoken from the</hi> Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>my Truth, mine Out-caſts, dwell with you, ſaith the Lord know it in your own particulars, the Light which makes manifeſt; the Chriſt which ſhews you all ye have done; Be ye a Covert to them from the face of the ſpoiler;</hi> For, <hi>yet a little while, and the Extortioner is at an end, the Spoiler ceaſeth, and the Oppreſſors are conſumed out of the Land: And in Mercy ſhall the Throne be eſtabliſhed, and he ſhall ſit upon it in Truth, whoſe Right it is, in the Tabernacle of David, judging and ſeeking Judgement, and haſtening Righteouſneſs. The Zeal of the Lord of Hoſts ſhall perform this;</hi> Of <hi>whom I am moved in much</hi> love, and bowels, and tenderneſs, <hi>thus</hi> to write; and <hi>from whoſe mouth I have written,</hi> that <hi>it may be well with you,</hi> if <hi>ye heed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29825:15"/> and do it:</hi> If <hi>otherwiſe, ye will be left without excuſe in that Day that is at hand, wherein he that ſearcheth the heart, and trieth the Keins, will render to every man according to his work.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>GEO. BISHOPE.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Briſtol,</hi> 
                     <date>the 12. of the third Mon. (cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>May,</hi> 1659.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>This <hi>following LETTER</hi> was for the <hi>Council of State,</hi> directed and ſent to a <hi>Member</hi> thereof, and of the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Friend,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>MAjor <hi>Dawbone</hi> returned yeſterday in the evening, with his Party, having viſited <hi>Bathe,</hi> and <hi>Lambsdown,</hi> and <hi>Baſſets</hi>-Houſe, and <hi>Freſhford</hi> in <hi>Somerſet,</hi> and <hi>Bradford</hi> in <hi>Wilts,</hi> and croſt the Countrey again to <hi>Stroudwater,</hi> and <hi>Painſwick</hi> in <hi>Gloceſterſhire,</hi> and <hi>Malmsbury,</hi> which was much to the terrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Enemy, who diſperſed themſelves, and dared not to ſtand or appear, and the reviving of <hi>your</hi> Friends in thoſe parts in this <hi>his</hi> March, which was about one hundred Miles to and again, <hi>he</hi> neither ſaw nor left any Party of them (as he could hear of, for he ſought them diligently, and marching by night) in thoſe Countreys, but found not the <hi>ſpirits</hi> of men <hi>ſo</hi> ſubdued, as that <hi>they</hi> were not <hi>ready</hi> to riſe, if the <hi>bond</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> were taken off <hi>them,</hi> and there ſhould appear a reaſonable encouragement, which ſpeaks a neceſſity of the expeditious and continual marching of your Horſe up and down in all parts, eſpecially where theſe inſurrections have been, and that ye give orders for that purpoſes, leaſt (as <hi>I</hi> have wrote) theſe ſcattered parties get time to draw together (the moſt deſperate of them) and lay the foundation of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother War, into which the reſt may flow, and ſo put ye to extremity for Force and Money, ere ye have time to breath for the ſecurity of the Common-wealth: And this let me
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:29825:15"/> tell <hi>you,</hi> that had not the <hi>Lord confounded them by his Power before, and perſecuted them by his Tempeſts that Night, the winde and rain fighting againſt them,</hi> and cauſed <hi>Maſſey</hi> to be taken, of which <hi>they</hi> had notice, (though he was ſuffered to eſcape) and given <hi>timely</hi> diſcovery, and broken <hi>their</hi> ſpirits, in which the <hi>Lord</hi> onely is ſeen) the <hi>Countrey</hi> had generally flowed in as one man from <hi>all</hi> parts, on this place, and <hi>thoſe</hi> here had generally roſe with <hi>them,</hi> and <hi>your</hi> Intereſt <hi>here</hi> by this time, had (in <hi>all</hi> probabil ty) <hi>been extinct,</hi> if not <hi>totally</hi> hazarded by reaſon thereof, throughout <hi>this</hi> Nation, and (as <hi>I</hi> have ſaid) ſhould the <hi>Lord</hi> but withdraw <hi>his</hi> band upon <hi>them,</hi> (ſo <hi>wonderful</hi> it is to ſee how <hi>they</hi> are chained and tormented) would be ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly in the ſame reſolution. Therefore it concerns <hi>you</hi> whilſt <hi>ye</hi> have time, to bear down <hi>this</hi> enemy, and ſo to ſecure <hi>places</hi> neceſſary for defence, and the <hi>Countrey,</hi> that <hi>this</hi> ſpirit get not up again, and put <hi>you</hi> to <hi>new</hi> diverſions. And ſeeing that the <hi>Arm</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> hath thus <hi>inexpreſſibly</hi> delivered <hi>you,</hi> and given <hi>your</hi> enemies <hi>once</hi> more into <hi>your</hi> hands for <hi>his deſpiſed peoples ſake, ſee that ye improve it for, and not againſt him and thoſe his people; and the doing Juſtice on thoſe whom he hath given into your hands, leaſt out of this Serpents egg do come a Cockatrice, and his fruit he a fiery-flying Serpent, and the Lord deliver you and your Forces into the Power of thoſe who ſeek the deſtruction of you and your Intereſt.</hi> And beware of falling under <hi>this</hi> ſpirit, or of thinking that the <hi>Breach</hi> between you can be <hi>healed:</hi> For <hi>I</hi> declare it to <hi>you from the Lord,</hi> That <hi>it is irreconcilable; it cannot, it will not be healed; yea, the Day will come, and now is, wherein it will be ſaid, We would have healed Babylon, but ſhe would not be healed; Let us depart every one to his own place.</hi> Therefore in the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Dread</hi> or the <hi>Almighty, ſtand,</hi> and <hi>bear</hi> over <hi>it, cruſh it to pieces, ſtamp it to powder; ſo ye will find it to crumble as the Clay, and fall before you as the Mire of the Streets:</hi> But <hi>if ye fear it, and becauſe of its afflicting you, and that</hi> it <hi>may not afflict you, ye ſacrifice to their Gods, and a1fflict the People of the Lord, and offer up his Sons and his Daughters in Sacrifice, cauſing them to paſs through the fire, through ſufferings
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:29825:16"/> for the pacifying of it.</hi> Be it known unto <hi>you from the Lord, it ſhall proſper againſt you, and leave you neither</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>What is become of</hi> thoſe <hi>in</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Council, <hi>and</hi> Army, <hi>to whom</hi> this <hi>was</hi> principally <hi>intended? what</hi> Place <hi>or</hi> Intereſt <hi>is now left</hi> them? <hi>I ſpeak not to</hi> upbraid them <hi>in the leaſt, or to</hi> inſult <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> them, <hi>the</hi> Lord <hi>is</hi> my <hi>witneſs, I mourn for</hi> them, <hi>but that the</hi> Lord may be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, whoſe word he <hi>hath</hi> fulfilled.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Is not</hi> the life of him and his People gone for its life, <hi>whom</hi> he and they let go out of their hand? <hi>Is not</hi> the King of Iſrael gone home to his Houſe heavy and diſpleaſed? <hi>As I wrote to them in the</hi> Name <hi>of the</hi> Lord, <hi>telling</hi> him <hi>and</hi> them, <hi>that</hi> it ſhould be ſo, <hi>and that</hi> is was Faithfulneſs <hi>in</hi> me to tell them or him ſo, <hi>and that</hi> we would be to me <hi>if</hi> I ſhould not, being required of the Lord, of whom I had received it, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the King of Iſrael might take it, and go home to his Houſe heavy and diſpleaſed; <hi>yea, that they</hi> knew the ſtory, <hi>and that</hi> they ſhould read and apply it to themſelves in the caſe, they who were concerned, who had done that thing; for it was their porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſhould aſſuredly come upon them from the Lord. <hi>See</hi> Mene Tekel, <hi>pag. 39, 40</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Again, are they not</hi> bowed down, and humbled? <hi>Is not</hi> their laſt done? <hi>Are not</hi> their Locks off? <hi>Are</hi> they not <hi>bound? and have not</hi> they bound themſelves? <hi>Can</hi> they work any more ſuch deliverance in the earth for themſelves or their Countrey, as hath been through their hands? <hi>Muſt it not</hi> (now) come from another place? <hi>Are they not</hi> ſubmitted? <hi>and have they not</hi> ſubmitted themſelves? <hi>Are they not</hi> lowr'd, <hi>and have they not</hi> brought themſelves low, and their friends, and the Cauſe of liberty of Conſcience, even to the ground, to the duſt? Do <hi>not</hi> their Maſters put them to grind at their pleaſure? Do they not dishand and do with them as they will? And when they have gone forth, when affliction is on them, and ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ck themſelves as heretofore; have they not found the Cauſe, (which whenſoever they brought it in their hand, &amp; could ſay of a truth, Lord here is the Cauſe, he never failed to deliver them, what ever were their ſtreights and difficulties.) I ſay, have they not found their Cauſe, their Locks, their Power gone, &amp; themſelves bound as with Fetters of Braſs? <hi>Is any</hi> ſtrength left in them. <hi>Yea, is not</hi> their Kingdom rent from them, and given to a Neighbor of theirs that is better then they, even to David, <hi>according as I ſpake to, and warned</hi> them <hi>from the</hi> Lord, <hi>that</hi> ſo <hi>it</hi> was, <hi>and</hi> ſo they <hi>ſhould find it.</hi> Me. Tek. <hi>p. 40, 41, 42, 43. Let</hi> God <hi>be</hi> glorified, <hi>and</hi> all <hi>men</hi> fear <hi>and</hi> tremble before him. Righteous art thou O Lord, juſt and true are thy wayes, O thou King of Saints; who would not fear and tremble before thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thy judgements are made manifeſt?</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>place nor Intereſt.</hi> From the <hi>Lord God Almighty (whoſe power wrought, and yet works through me for the confounding of the Enemy in this his bloody deſign against inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent People and the Common-wealth,</hi> (for its laid <hi>all</hi> on <hi>them,</hi> as if <hi>they</hi> had deſigned the <hi>ſhedding</hi> of the <hi>blood</hi> of <hi>theſe) who watcht over you when</hi> ye <hi>ſlept, &amp; had regard to your ſafety for his Peoples ſake, when ye knew not the depth and nearneſs of your dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger) am I moved thus to write, that ye may be warned and left without excuſe in the day when theſe things ſhall befall you, which will not be long if ye ſhall ſo turn it;</hi> for verily <hi>I</hi> ſee <hi>them</hi> (in <hi>that</hi> which is not of <hi>this</hi> world) <hi>all</hi> deſperately bent againſt <hi>you,</hi> and ready to over-run <hi>you,</hi> ſhould <hi>He</hi> but withdraw <hi>his</hi> hand which yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains <hi>them,</hi> even (<hi>ſome</hi> of <hi>them) almoſt</hi> to diſtraction: <hi>And withdraw he will, if ye turn this great Deliverance (which was for) againſt his People:</hi> Which that it may never be by <hi>you,</hi> O how are <hi>my</hi> bowels turned within <hi>me. My dear</hi> Friends, for
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29825:16"/> 
                  <hi>your</hi> ſake, that ſo the <hi>Lord</hi> may never have cauſe to reckon with <hi>you</hi> on <hi>this</hi> account. But if it ſo be, <hi>the will of the Lord be done, He</hi> will be a <hi>City of Refuge</hi> for <hi>His</hi> People, and thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <hi>you</hi> who in faithfulneſs diſcharge <hi>your</hi> own ſouls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right to <hi>him</hi> againſt <hi>ſuch</hi> proceedings, will find a <hi>hiding place in the day of his fierce wrath, which is haſtening upon the heall of the wicked.</hi> The <hi>time</hi> draweth <hi>nigh; Bleſſed are all they who in that day ſhall be found written in the Lambs Book of Life.</hi> In <hi>Bowels</hi> of <hi>love,</hi> and <hi>truth</hi> or <hi>heart,</hi> as <hi>foreſeeing the things that are at hand, yea at the door,</hi> and in obedience to the <hi>Lord</hi> have <hi>I</hi> thus written.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>George Biſhope.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Briſtol,</hi> 
                     <date>the 6th. of the 6th. Mon. 1659.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another <hi>Letter</hi> ſent to a <hi>Member</hi> of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>State.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Friend,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have formerly writ to <hi>thee</hi> concerning the <hi>Affairs</hi> of the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> as opportunity preſented: The occaſion of <hi>this</hi> is in reference to <hi>theſe</hi> our <hi>New-Engliſh</hi> Friends, the <hi>Bearers</hi> hereof, late of, and near the <hi>Town</hi> of <hi>Salem</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> who having paſſed through the <hi>rigorous</hi> execution of <hi>their</hi> cruel Laws, as to <hi>Impriſonments, Whippings, Scourgings, Confiſcation, and Sale of their Goods and Eſtates,</hi> are at length <hi>baniſhed</hi> upon <hi>pain</hi> of <hi>death,</hi> which is <hi>their</hi> ſtate at <hi>this</hi> preſent, having not above <hi>four</hi> dayes time to tranſport <hi>themſelves</hi> for <hi>England,</hi> whither to come, and to ſpread the <hi>mercileſs</hi> ſufferings of <hi>them</hi> and <hi>their</hi> Friends before <hi>thoſe</hi> in Authority, it lay upon <hi>them</hi> from the Lord, for which purpoſe <hi>they</hi> are arrived here, and are now paſſing for <hi>London,</hi> to unload themſelves of <hi>their</hi> heavy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then before the <hi>Parliament,</hi> to whom, or to ſuch as <hi>they</hi> ſhall appoint, <hi>they</hi> (with <hi>their friends</hi> and <hi>fellow-ſufferers</hi> in <hi>England</hi>) are able and ready? what by <hi>Copies</hi> of <hi>their Laws,</hi> and the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:29825:17"/> of <hi>Baniſhment</hi> (which <hi>they</hi> have under the <hi>Secretaries</hi> own hand, and the <hi>manner of proſecutions,</hi> as to <hi>apprehenſions, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, fines, diſtreſſes, ſcourgings, whippings, beatings, cutting off of ears, burnings, ſelling for Bondmen and Bondwomen</hi> in <hi>other</hi> Plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to make appear ſuch <hi>Monſtrous</hi> cruelties as <hi>England</hi> hath not known before <hi>this</hi> day to have proceeded out of <hi>it,</hi> much leſs from <hi>ſuch</hi> as <hi>once ſuffered,</hi> and <hi>quitted their Native Countrey becauſe of Conſcience,</hi> which makes <hi>it</hi> the <hi>more</hi> to be admired; and <hi>all this</hi> for <hi>no</hi> other cauſe but <hi>their</hi> Conſcience to <hi>God,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>they</hi> cannot come to <hi>their Worſhips,</hi> and eat the <hi>ſacrifices of ſuch men of Blood;</hi> becauſe <hi>they meet together to wait upon the Lord, and ſpeak to one another to fear God:</hi> Becauſe <hi>they entertain ſtrangers,</hi> and <hi>receive the ſervants of the Lord into their Houſes:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>they are ſuch</hi> as are called <hi>Quakers,</hi> whom <hi>without</hi> warrant to <hi>apprehend,</hi> even upon ſuſpition that <hi>they</hi> are ſuch, and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon, power</hi> is given to <hi>their</hi> Officers; and againſt whom in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to <hi>all their barbarous</hi> executions, <hi>they</hi> have not <hi>ſo</hi> much as with <hi>one</hi> of <hi>them</hi> proceeded according to <hi>due</hi> order or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in <hi>Law,</hi> but with <hi>rage</hi> and <hi>cruelty,</hi> and with a <hi>high and ſtrong hand</hi> endeavour and determine (as <hi>themſelves</hi> have ſaid) yea, in <hi>open Court</hi> have not been aſhamed to <hi>declare</hi>) becauſe <hi>they have power in their hands</hi> to <hi>wear out, cut off</hi> from, and <hi>expel</hi> the <hi>Countrey this</hi> whole Generation.</p>
               <p>The conſideration whereof, and what may be the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of <hi>this,</hi> as to the <hi>body</hi> of <hi>friends</hi> there, (<hi>in whoſe</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">On the <hi>27.</hi> of the <hi>8.</hi> Month, <hi>1659.</hi> the Government of <hi>Maſſathuſets</hi> Bay in <hi>New England,</hi> murdered at <hi>Boſton</hi> viz <hi>VVil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Robinſon,</hi> and <hi>Marmaduke Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venſon,</hi> two ſervants of the Lord, whom <hi>they slew,</hi> and <hi>hung upon a Tree,</hi> for no other cauſe but for <hi>their conſcience</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> being <hi>legally</hi> convicted of <hi>no one</hi> Opinion or Practice, but were put to <hi>death</hi> barely for being ſuch as the <hi>world</hi> calls Quakers, and coming into <hi>their</hi> Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whoſe <hi>innocent</hi> Blood cryes aloud to the <hi>Lord</hi> for Vengeance, who will aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bring it upon them, and it haſtens: For ſuch a <hi>Barbarous piece of murderous cruelty,</hi> (throughly circumſtantiated) was never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eard of, being from men who ſted their Native Countrey <hi>becauſe</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> on their Countrey men for <hi>their conſcience,</hi> who ſtood it out to the <hi>death, (glory</hi> to the Lord for ever, who was near them) but their bloody perſecuters (when in <hi>old</hi> England) could not look ſo much as a <hi>Priſon</hi> in the face But of this a particular Relation may ſhortly be made publick.</note> 
                  <hi>blood ere this time they may have imbrued their hands</hi>) and <hi>this</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and as to <hi>you</hi> who are in <hi>Authority,</hi> ſhould ſuch <hi>Bloodſheds, Murthers, Rapines</hi> and <hi>Cruelties</hi> be ſuffered in <hi>your</hi> Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, hath filled <hi>my</hi> heart with <hi>griefe</hi> and <hi>ſorrow;</hi> and in the <hi>depth</hi> of <hi>my</hi> ſpirit am <hi>I moved of the Lord, the Maker of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, in whom is the breath of all men, to write to thee about it,</hi> who haſt been <hi>ſometime</hi> Governor of <hi>that</hi> Countrey,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29825:17"/> and knoweſt <hi>their</hi> manners and powers, and the <hi>cruelty</hi> of <hi>their</hi> ſpirits, and art eminent in Authority in <hi>this</hi> Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, that <hi>thou mayeſt conſider and lay it to heart, and be zealous for the deliverance of thoſe who have no helper;</hi> for which purpoſe I have encloſed to <hi>thee their</hi> Addreſs to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> which <hi>thou</hi> art deſired to help into the <hi>Houſe,</hi> and by <hi>ſuch</hi> ways and means, and with <hi>ſuch</hi> Members to proceed and work, as <hi>thou</hi> ſhalt think fit, for the <hi>more</hi> ſpeedy and effectual accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>what</hi> therein is <hi>juſtly</hi> deſired, and is <hi>requiſite</hi> in the <hi>caſe.</hi> I am not unſenſible of the multitude of buſineſs which throngs in upon <hi>thee</hi> for the <hi>Publick</hi> in <hi>this</hi> hour, nor of the burthens <hi>thou</hi> beareſt in reference to <hi>that,</hi> and the <hi>ſpirit</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <hi>you</hi> that hinders the doing of what <hi>ye</hi> would for <hi>honeſt</hi> men, and the <hi>Commonwealth:</hi> Nor of the <hi>Croſs</hi> that is to be endured in undertaking a thing of <hi>this</hi> nature; but when <hi>I</hi> conſider that it is the <hi>Eternal Truth of God</hi> in <hi>them,</hi> for, and becauſe of which <hi>they</hi> ſuffer; which <hi>Truth muſt (and the time is at hand, when the meaſure of ſufferings is full, which haſtens) reign over all; (the Zeal of the Lord of Hoſts ſhall perform it.)</hi> And when <hi>I</hi> conſider how the <hi>Lord</hi> tenders <hi>his Truth</hi> and <hi>ſuffering-people,</hi> even <hi>as the apple of his Eye,</hi> and will not ſuffer a <hi>Cup of cold wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter given to a Diſciple in the Name of a Diſciple, to go without a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples reward: Foraſmuch as ye have done it unto one of the leaſt of theſe my Brethren, will the Son of man ſay, (and the hour is near) when he ſhall reign in his Glory, and ſit on the Throne of his Glory, and all the holy Angels with him:) ye did it unto me.</hi> And when <hi>I</hi> conſider what need <hi>every</hi> man will have of the <hi>Mercy</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> in the <hi>day when he ſhall ſeperate the ſheep from the Goats, and ſay to the ſheep on his right hand, Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you before the foundation of the world. And to the Goats on his left hand, Depart from me ye curſed, into everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels,</hi> which is <hi>at the door.</hi> And when <hi>I</hi> mind the <hi>movings</hi> of <hi>God</hi> that <hi>is</hi> upon <hi>me, I</hi> am <hi>preſſed in ſpirit</hi> to render <hi>this</hi> unto thee, that <hi>thou</hi> mayeſt have <hi>thy</hi> reward in the <hi>day which is nigh, wherein the Righteous God ſhall render to every man according to his works.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:29825:18"/>
               <p>Therefore <hi>dear Friend,</hi> let <hi>this my Requeſt be acceptable unto thee,</hi> and what in <hi>thee</hi> lyes, do in the behalf of <hi>theſe poor, deſpiſed, ſuffering People,</hi> the <hi>Lord's</hi> Baniſhed, who are appointed as <hi>Sheep for the ſlaughter,</hi> and <hi>for Gods ſake are killed all the day long; and are beaten, and made to cry by Reaſon of the Oppreſſor:</hi> That ſo the <hi>Bleſſing of the God of Abraham may reſt upon thee and thy Poſterity for ever.</hi> For this <hi>I</hi> know, That the <hi>Day is at hand</hi> wherein if <hi>man</hi> ſhall not, yet the <hi>Lord</hi> will <hi>thoroughly plead the Cauſe of his People;</hi> and <hi>then thoſe who have ſhut their ears at the cry of the poor and needy; when they cry in their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity, the Lord</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>The</hi> Caſe <hi>of</hi> theſe ſuffering <hi>friends, was preſented to the</hi> Council <hi>of</hi> State <hi>by</hi> that <hi>Member of the</hi> Council <hi>and</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>to whom</hi> it <hi>was wrote, it being judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that ſo to do, was the</hi> quickeſt <hi>expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in a</hi> matter <hi>of</hi> ſuch <hi>weight and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence as the</hi> Eſtates, Liberties, <hi>&amp;</hi> Lives <hi>of</hi> ſo <hi>many Families of</hi> people <hi>who</hi> fear the Lord; <hi>which</hi> they <hi>took into conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but paſſed away,</hi> re infecta, <hi>without doing any thing,</hi> as alſo <hi>did the</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (<hi>who were ſhut out of</hi> their <hi>houſe the</hi> 12th. <hi>of the</hi> Month <hi>following) to the</hi> Speaker <hi>of</hi> which, <hi>and</hi> many <hi>of the</hi> Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, <hi>ſeveral Abſtracts of the</hi> cruel whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings, impriſonments, beatings, confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation <hi>of</hi> Eſtates, Burning, <hi>and</hi> cutting off <hi>of the</hi> Ears <hi>of</hi> many innocent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>were delivered ſometime before by the hands of ſome of the</hi> chiefeſt <hi>ſufferers. There is yet a little time for them that remain in Power, to hear the</hi> Cry of the poor and needy, <hi>and</hi> to deliver them who are appointed to dye, <hi>leaſt the</hi> Lord refuſe to hear them in the Day of their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity, <hi>and ſo</hi> this <hi>his</hi> Word <hi>be fulfilled upon</hi> them.</note> 
                  <hi>will not hear them.</hi> So to <hi>that</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>thee</hi> which <hi>mourns with them that mourn, and weeps with thoſe who weep,</hi> and <hi>ſuffers with them that are in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, as being in the body, I</hi> commend, and leave <hi>this</hi> thing, and remain</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Thy Friend</hi> in the <hi>Bowels</hi> and <hi>Compaſſion</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus, GEO. BISHOPE.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Briſtol,</hi> 
                     <date>the 20. of the 7th. Mon. 1659.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:29825:18"/>
               <head>To the <hi>General Council</hi> of the <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>ARMY,</hi> and <hi>thoſe</hi> with <hi>them</hi> who are <hi>now</hi> conſulting the <hi>good</hi> of the COMMON-WEALTH.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Friends,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF</hi> ye <hi>mean to proſper, or that the</hi> Lord <hi>be with</hi> you <hi>as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore; with</hi> his <hi>preſence to help</hi> you <hi>out of all</hi> your <hi>ſtreights and Difficulties,</hi> Purge out from amongſt you the ſpirit of the ſixth Article of your late<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Here lyes the</hi> bottom <hi>of</hi> their <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage, and the</hi> very ground <hi>and</hi> cauſe <hi>of all</hi> their <hi>miſery; For having by the</hi> ſixth Article of their Addreſs <hi>preſented the</hi> Parliament May <hi>12. 1659.</hi> Point blank changed the Cauſe of Liberty of Conſcience, Viz From the Good Old one, to a New Bad One; from that which at firſt, and all along they engaged in, and for, and declared to that which they engaged againſt; <hi>which whileſt</hi> they engaged againſt <hi>in the</hi> behalf <hi>of</hi> Liberty of Conſcience, (<hi>the</hi> Dominion of God) he never failed to deliver them, what ever were their ſtraits and difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; <hi>and ſo having drawn forth</hi> their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, <hi>after ſo</hi> wonderful <hi>a Deliverance, againſt</hi> their Declarations, (<hi>as I lately ſhewed them from the</hi> Lord <hi>in</hi> the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing, Mene Tek<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l, <hi>which</hi> he <hi>cauſed</hi> me <hi>to draw againſt</hi> them, <hi>wherein</hi> they were weighed in the Ballance, <hi>and</hi> found want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) their Kingdom <hi>became</hi> divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it ſelf, <hi>and was</hi> numbred, <hi>and is</hi> fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. <hi>Nevertheleſs the</hi> Lord gave them therein time <hi>and</hi> ſpace of Repentance, <hi>and</hi> this <hi>other</hi> Day <hi>alſo, wherein</hi> he <hi>war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> them, <hi>as in</hi> this <hi>letter, being</hi> loath to give them up, who had been the Sword of his Excellency and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of his ſtrength, by whom he had wrought ſuch wonderful Deliverances, in which <hi>he</hi> was <hi>glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d,</hi> but <hi>they not heeding,</hi> this <hi>their</hi> day paſſed over <hi>alſo</hi> in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as is b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yond the <hi>wonders</hi> of the <hi>twenty</hi> years preceding, which made the <hi>earth to tremble:</hi> And although <hi>ſome</hi> of <hi>them</hi> when <hi>they</hi> ſaw the <hi>waters</hi> flowing over <hi>their</hi> heads, came again to the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and placed <hi>liberty of Conſcience</hi> in the 7th. <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>ten</hi> Particulars, agreed on by <hi>them</hi> as the thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h (it is ſaid) <hi>they</hi> were Reſolved to live and dye; in the very words of the <hi>third Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>icl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ement</hi> which <hi>I</hi> produced againſt the ſixth Article of <hi>their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs,</hi> in proof of my cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> upon <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m,</hi> that they had Point-blank changed the Cauſe, there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying the Lord and <hi>me</hi> in what <hi>I</hi> had ſo charged upon <hi>them</hi> from <hi>his</hi> mouth, and condemning them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elves; yet it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>heir</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ur was over. And ſo he who led into capti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ity is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed into c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he who k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d with t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſword is killed by the ſword; He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s the pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ience and faith of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>s.</note> Addreſs to the Parliament, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is againſt Liberty of Conſcience, the Dominion of God, which he hath owned, and will own, and ſet over all; <hi>ſo</hi> ſhall ye proſper, the Lord hath ſpoken it. <hi>If</hi> otherwiſe, <hi>and that upon</hi> Political, or other ends, ye cheriſh that ſpirit, or ſuffer it to live, or act, or be in you, or oppreſs the People of the Lord, or of the Land, and ſo by an evil or an heart of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, ye again depart from the living God who hath once more delivered you, <hi>know</hi> this <hi>from the</hi> Lord, Ye cannot proſper<note n="†" place="margin">This con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded them, (they <hi>not heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in this their hour) and then <hi>was no reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy;</hi> the word of the Lord is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill'd upon them</note>; <hi>for</hi> he is come to reign whoſe Right it is, of the encreaſe of whoſe Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Peace, there ſhall be no end; Upon the Throne of David, to order it, and to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh it with Judgement, and with Juſtice, from henceforth even for ever: The Zeale of the Lord of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29825:19"/> Hoſts ſhall perform this, and the hour is at hand: <hi>Therefore</hi> my dear friends, let this my Counſel be acceptable unto you, and break off your ſins by righteouſneſs, and your iniquities by ſhewing mercy to the poor, if it may be a lengthening of your tranquillity: <hi>For</hi> from the Lord God Almighty, (<hi>the</hi> Angel of whoſe preſence <hi>went before</hi> you, <hi>and hath been</hi> your <hi>Rereguard</hi>) am I moved thus to write; <hi>who</hi> am <hi>known to</hi> you <hi>by the Name of</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Geo. Biſhope.</signed>
                  <dateline>Briſtol, <date>
                        <hi>the</hi> 16th. <hi>of the</hi> 8th. <hi>Month, 1659. in the</hi> Morning.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another <hi>Letter</hi> ſent to a <hi>Citizen</hi> of <hi>LONDON,</hi> and a <hi>Commiſſioner</hi> of the MILITIA <hi>there.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Friend,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received <hi>thy</hi> Letter, and <hi>thy</hi> Love; by this time (<hi>I</hi> ſuppoſe) <hi>thou</hi> haſt an anſwer in <hi>thy</hi> ſelf, as to the deſire of <hi>my</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up; ſeeing that the <hi>General Council</hi> of <hi>Officers</hi> have not laid the <hi>Baſis</hi> of <hi>their</hi> Government in <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs;</hi> but in the <hi>mixtures</hi> of <hi>corrupt</hi> and <hi>bad</hi> Intereſts, and the <hi>men</hi> of <hi>each,</hi> which <hi>God hath curſed,</hi> and not onely ſo, but have quickened <hi>their</hi> ſtrange compoſition with the<note n="*" place="margin">Their decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for the Prieſts, &amp; cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or falling under the ſpirit that roſe up a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt them, was that which ſlew them.</note> 
                  <hi>black ſpirit</hi> of <hi>that</hi> generation, <hi>who from the beginning</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Time hath, &amp; doth, and will make this moſt manifeſt.</note> 
                  <hi>hitherto hath been, and from henceforth will be the deſtruction of all who are ſwayed by it.</hi> So <hi>this</hi> gives rather a reaſon of <hi>my</hi> ſilence, then that <hi>I</hi> have (as yet) any thing upon <hi>me</hi> to move to <hi>you</hi>-ward, Indeed <hi>I</hi> muſt ſay, <hi>This</hi> laſt turn was alſo of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and at the <hi>very</hi> time of it when <hi>I</hi> had heard nothing by the <hi>hearing of the ear; I</hi> bore and went thorough as of <hi>them that</hi> went before) the travel thereof, and, the <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> wrought in,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:29825:19"/> and thorough me, to the accompliſhing of <hi>this</hi> thing, Which<note n="*" place="margin">For being ſo cloſely purſued, preſently upon their Return from defeating <hi>G. Booth,</hi> what other thing could be expected but their utmoſt endeavours for the preſervation of themſelves; and how otherwiſe could that be done but by the laying aſide of thoſe who gave the Proſecution.</note> 
                  <hi>deſperate</hi> neceſſity on the <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers</hi> part, and the <hi>juſt</hi> † hand of the <hi>Lord</hi> on the <hi>Parliament,</hi> who had <hi>their Day,</hi> and miſuſed <hi>it,</hi> hath <hi>conſtrained.</hi> But what? was it that <hi>they</hi> might <hi>take</hi> up, and <hi>Court</hi> the <hi>accurſed</hi> thing, and <hi>cloſe</hi> with the <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Intereſts, whom God had ſpewd out,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">In particular, the <hi>buſineſs</hi> of <hi>Tythes,</hi> with which <hi>they</hi> never before <hi>yoked</hi> the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> (I ſay the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth)</hi> but left <hi>it</hi> hanging on the <hi>pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant</hi> Twig of the <hi>Statute</hi> for <hi>trebble da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages,</hi> which was ready to fall with <hi>its</hi> own <hi>weight,</hi> the <hi>weight</hi> whereof, and of the cruel ſufferings of the Generality of the People of theſe Nations, (except the <hi>Intereſted,</hi> and <hi>their</hi> creatures) by reaſon of <hi>Tythes,</hi> particularly the <hi>People</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> in their <hi>Perſons, Eſtates,</hi> and <hi>lives,</hi> was <hi>ſo</hi> great, and the <hi>cry ſo loud,</hi> that the <hi>Parliament</hi> upon <hi>their very</hi> firſt ſitting after <hi>their</hi> interruption, as a <hi>Retribution</hi> to the <hi>Lord</hi> for <hi>their wonderful</hi> return, did appoint among <hi>their firſt</hi> things, a <hi>Committee</hi> of <hi>their</hi> own Members to ſend for the Sufferers <hi>then</hi> in <hi>Priſon,</hi> to <hi>examine their</hi> reſpective Caſes, and to make report of <hi>them</hi> to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> which upon <hi>examination</hi> appeared ſo <hi>hard</hi> and <hi>foul,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the <hi>laws</hi> by which <hi>they</hi> ſuffered, the <hi>witneſſe</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> in <hi>them</hi> anſwering to the cry of <hi>theſe</hi> ſufferings, that <hi>they</hi> though fit to <hi>ſet them</hi> at <hi>liberty,</hi> and not to remand <hi>them</hi> to their <hi>old</hi> captivities, which is a witneſs againſt <hi>themſelves</hi> in the caſe, unto wch anſwereth the witneſs of <hi>God</hi> in them, which is <hi>greater then all,</hi> and will be <hi>their</hi> great cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mnation. Now for the <hi>Parliament</hi> to <hi>exact</hi> the <hi>payment</hi> of <hi>Tythes</hi> in <hi>ſuch</hi> a time and ſeaſon as by <hi>theſe their</hi> own proceedings, gave <hi>honeſt</hi> men every where <hi>reaſonable</hi> cauſe to expect <hi>their utter</hi> taking away; for <hi>them</hi> to eſtabliſh <hi>thoſe very</hi> Laws for <hi>Tythes</hi> by which <hi>thoſe</hi> conſcientious men ſuffered, which <hi>laws they</hi> ſo judged in appointing a <hi>Committee</hi> of <hi>their</hi> own to ſend for the <hi>priſoners,</hi> and examine <hi>their</hi> caſes, who ſuffered by <hi>thoſe</hi> laws; which Priſoners ſo ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ring by thoſe laws, <hi>thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee ſo ſet at liberty as aforeſaid, and to <hi>or er</hi> the <hi>Judges</hi> to cauſe ſuch their Order to be read in the Courts at the ſeveral aſſiz Sin <hi>this</hi> Nation by which the ſame People were rendered into a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of ſufferring a new by theſe very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aws which by <hi>their</hi> former proceedings the Parliament had judg'd ſo gri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vous, and <hi>this</hi> in the behalf of a <hi>generation</hi> of men who had been even <hi>then deſigning</hi> againſt <hi>them</hi> throughout this Naion, by <hi>Plot</hi> and <hi>Force</hi> to have overturned <hi>them,</hi> againſt <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> generation who had ſtood by <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m</hi> in that great hour, and were very much inſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umental in the overturning of thoſe deſigns, who alſo had been <hi>alw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>yes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>heir ſure, tryed,</hi> and conſtant <hi>Friends,</hi> which the <hi>others</hi> were not, (<hi>moſt</hi> of <hi>them)</hi> but the contrary. <hi>This</hi> was <hi>that</hi> which diſpleaſed the Lord, being an <hi>ill</hi> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>quital of that <hi>their</hi> wond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rful deliverance for the ſake of thoſe his people, and cauſed (among <hi>other</hi> things) his juſt hand to bring that <hi>Turn upon them,</hi> of which <hi>I</hi> am a witn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſs, even of the curſe of the Lord, which paſſed thorough <hi>me</hi> againſt <hi>them,</hi> upon that their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution.</note> 
                  <hi>and pointed at with the moſt legible Characters of overturning and Blood, as thoſe, and that which he abhorred;</hi> and ſo <hi>lay</hi> a bottom for <hi>their</hi> ſtation, in <hi>that</hi> unto which is <hi>his</hi> ſore diſpleaſure; That the <hi>Lord</hi> hath given <hi>them</hi> the <hi>great</hi> deliverance: Or, that <hi>they</hi> ſhould have obſerved the direction of <hi>his</hi> provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in laying aſide of <hi>ſuch</hi> Men and things, and the narrowing of <hi>All</hi> to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:29825:20"/> 
                  <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> the end of <hi>his</hi> workings, and unto <hi>that</hi> have taken heed, and on <hi>that</hi> Baſis to have raiſed in <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty</hi> and <hi>Juſtice, ſuch</hi> a <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Commmwealth as God would bleſs.</hi> Surely <hi>theſe</hi> men, the <hi>laſt</hi> and <hi>beſt</hi> of <hi>them</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, have had <hi>their Day wherein to know, and to do the things that belong unto their Peace, and the good of the Commonwealth,</hi> which the <hi>Lord</hi> hath given <hi>them</hi> for <hi>that</hi> purpoſe, and to try <hi>them</hi> alſo, and to <hi>prove them,</hi> and to <hi>leave them without excuſe,</hi> who upon <hi>proof</hi> and <hi>tryal</hi> having already brought forth the <hi>Grapes</hi> of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and the <hi>Cluſters</hi> of <hi>Gomorrha;</hi> what now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth but a <hi>fearful expectation of the ſpeedy and final overthrow of the things that are, which already</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">This the Lord ſhewed <hi>me,</hi> even <hi>that the Parliament, Council of State, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners of Sequeſtrations,</hi> and <hi>the things that then were, were waxing old, and ready to Vaniſh;</hi> and that <hi>this</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of men, (the men <hi>then</hi> in <hi>power</hi>) were but as the <hi>laſt blinch</hi> of a Candle, and as a <hi>little lightening</hi> before <hi>death;</hi> and it is but a very little time, and they are wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en <hi>old,</hi> and vaniſhed, (the <hi>men then</hi> in power and conduct:) And ſo what <hi>he</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>me,</hi> hath the Lord ſoon fulfilled; to whom be glory for ever: The reſt <hi>he</hi> will aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accompliſh in <hi>its</hi> ſeaſon, and the <hi>hour</hi> is at hand; for <hi>it</hi> is <hi>that</hi> which will follow the Revolution of all theſe things, as certainly as are the Revolutions; which Revolutions <hi>he</hi> makes for the accompliſhing of it, and the things make haſte.</note> 
                  <hi>was old, and are ready to vaniſh,</hi> that <hi>he may reign whoſe Right it is; and he is come to reign whoſe is the Right, of the encreaſe of whoſe Government and Peace there ſhall be no end, upon the Throne of David, and upon his Kingdom, to order it, &amp; to eſtabliſh it with Juſtice and with Judgement, from henceforth even for ever:</hi> For <hi>He</hi> hath tryed <hi>all</hi> men, and found <hi>them</hi> wanting: <hi>He</hi> hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a <hi>Day</hi> to <hi>every ſort</hi> of <hi>men;</hi> but <hi>they</hi> have proved faulty, and have turned againſt <hi>Him; Therefore his own Arm will bring to himſelf Salvation, and his Fury ſhall ſuſtain him; and none but him, on whoſe ſhoulders the Government is laid, who is King of Righteouſneſs, and Prince of Peace, will he truſt to rule the Earth,</hi> after <hi>He</hi> hath brought man <hi>low,</hi> &amp; made <hi>him</hi> to appear as a <hi>thing</hi> of nought: For <hi>this</hi> purpoſe is <hi>he</hi> ſhaking <hi>not onely the Earth, but the Heavens alſo,</hi> and bringing <hi>great diſtreſs, tribulation and anguiſh, Clouds and thick darkneſs,</hi> even that the <hi>deſire of all Nations may come</hi> and take to <hi>himſelf</hi> the Dominion: And <hi>he is come, and is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to himſelf the Dominion, whoſe Kingdom is an everlaſting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and the Scepter of whoſe Kingdom is a Scepter of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:</hi> On whom <hi>we</hi> wait; in whom <hi>we</hi> truſt; who will be unto <hi>us</hi> a <hi>City of Refuge</hi> in the <hi>Day</hi> wherein he will <hi>puniſh the Hoſt of the high ones of the earth, and the Kings of the Earth, upon the earth,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:29825:20"/> and will gather them into a Pit:</hi> And the <hi>Sun ſhall be confounded, and the Moon abaſhed;</hi> then ſhall the <hi>Lord reign before his Ancients gloriouſly:</hi> And the <hi>Day is at hand,</hi> even the <hi>Day</hi> wherein the <hi>Lord will come in ten thouſands of his Saints, and will execute venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon all, and convince all that are ungodly among men, of all their ungodly deeds which they have ungodly committed; and of all their hard ſpeeches which ungodly ſinners have ſpoken againſt him; and every eye ſhall ſee him they alſo which have pierced him; and all kindreds of the Earth ſhall wail becauſe of him: Even ſo Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus <hi>my</hi> Friend, <hi>thou</hi> haſt ſome account of <hi>my</hi> ſpirit in <hi>this</hi> thing, to the end that <hi>thou,</hi> and the <hi>Honorable</hi> Woman from whom <hi>thou</hi> wroteſt, and <hi>her</hi> Husband, (<hi>my dear</hi> Friends, to whom is <hi>my</hi> Love) may ſee that <hi>I</hi> ſlight <hi>ye</hi> not, but that <hi>your</hi> kindneſs is accepted by</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your</hi> Friend in the <hi>Truth</hi> of <hi>God (now) made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manifeſt, George Biſhope.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Briſtol,</hi> 
                     <date>the 2d. of the 9th. Mon. 1659.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To <hi>thoſe</hi> in the <hi>Army</hi> and <hi>elſe where,</hi> who under the <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of the Night</hi> that is come upon <hi>them,</hi> do cry out, <hi>Watchman! What of the Night? Watchman! What of the night?</hi> Am <hi>I</hi> moved of the <hi>Lord</hi> to write, and it is to <hi>them</hi> the <hi>tender</hi> Viſitation of <hi>his</hi> Love. <hi>The BURDEN</hi> of <hi>DUMAH.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DUmah</hi> was one of the <hi>Cities</hi> of the <hi>Mountains,</hi> in the <hi>Land</hi> of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which fell by <hi>lot</hi> to the inheritance of the <hi>tribe</hi> of the <hi>children</hi> of <hi>Judah,</hi> ſituate among the <hi>uttermoſt</hi> Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties towards the <hi>coaſt</hi> of <hi>Edom,</hi> (which is <hi>Eſau, Jacob's</hi> elder Brother) and bearing the Name of <hi>Iſmaels ſixth</hi> Son, who was the Son of <hi>Hagar</hi> the <hi>bond-woman.</hi> In the <hi>night</hi> of the <hi>burden</hi> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> when the <hi>Watchman</hi> was ſet by the <hi>Commandment</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:29825:21"/> of the <hi>Lord</hi> to declare what <hi>he</hi> ſaw, after that <hi>he</hi> had ſeen a <hi>Chariot</hi> with a <hi>couple</hi> of <hi>Horſe-men;</hi> a <hi>Chariot</hi> of <hi>Aſſes,</hi> and a Chariot of <hi>Camels,</hi> and had hearkened <hi>diligently</hi> with <hi>much</hi> heed, and had cried like a <hi>Lyon, My Lord! I ſtand continually upon the watch in the day time, and I am ſet in my ward whole Nights, and behold there cometh a Chariot of Men with a couple of Horſe-men.</hi> And after <hi>he</hi> had anſwered and ſaid, <hi>Babylon is fallen, is fallen, and all the graven Images of her Gods he hath broken to the ground. O my Threſhing, and the Corn of my Floore! That which I have heard of the Lord of Hoſts, the God of Iſrael, have I declared unto you. He</hi> called to <hi>me</hi> out of <hi>Seir,</hi> (which is <hi>Edom,</hi> whither <hi>he</hi> was gone) <hi>Watchman! What of the Night? Watchman! What of the Night?</hi> (This in the <hi>Letter</hi> without, but read in the <hi>Spirit</hi> within.)</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Friend!</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>TO</hi> thy <hi>Call,</hi> Watchman! What of the night? Watchman? What of the night? I <hi>anſwer from the</hi> Lord.—The morning cometh, and alſo the night: If yee will enquire, Enquire yee:—Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn,—Come—</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The</hi> Moſt High GOD, who changes times and ſeaſons, and doth whatſoever hee pleaſeth in Heaven, and in the Earth; the Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>of</hi> Iſrael, who neither ſlumbers nor ſleepeth; <hi>who giveth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> all <hi>men a</hi> Day; <hi>to</hi> Nations, Kingdoms, States <hi>a</hi> Day, wherein to know and do the things that appertain unto their peace, <hi>hath given to the</hi> Army <hi>a</hi> Day; <hi>yea, a</hi> Day, <hi>and a</hi> Day, <hi>and hath raiſed</hi> them <hi>up from a</hi> Little <hi>one, a</hi> Deſpiſed <hi>one, into a</hi> Great Hoſt; <hi>and</hi> in bleſſing hath bleſſed them, <hi>and</hi> in multiplying hath multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, <hi>and hath proſpered</hi> them whitherſoever they <hi>went, and in</hi> whatſoever their <hi>hand found</hi> them <hi>to do, and hath laden</hi> them <hi>with</hi> victories, <hi>and gave to</hi> their<note n="*" place="margin">O. Cromwel.</note> 
                        <hi>General</hi> a Kingdom, and Majeſty, and Glory and Honor. And for the Majeſty that he gave him, all Nations trembled and feared before him; whom he would he ſlew, and whom he would, he kept alive: whom he would, he ſet up; and whom he would, he put down. But when his heart was lifted up, and his mind hardned in pride, <hi>the</hi> Lord cut him off, <hi>accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to</hi> † his <hi>word which</hi> he <hi>hath ſpoken by</hi> me.<note n="*" place="margin">See Letter to O. P. pag. <hi>14.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>And when</hi> his <hi>Son roſe up in</hi> his <hi>ſtead, and a</hi> Power <hi>under</hi> him <hi>ſeeking to do</hi> that, <hi>for which the</hi> Lord <hi>had cut off</hi> his <hi>father before</hi> him, He ſoon overturned him,<note n="*" place="margin">See Letter to R. P. pag. <hi>18.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>as</hi> I <hi>had writ to</hi> him <hi>in the</hi> name <hi>of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:29825:21"/> the</hi> Lord, <hi>and deliver</hi> all <hi>Power into</hi> your <hi>hands, whom</hi> he <hi>and</hi> his <hi>Power</hi> ſought <hi>to</hi> over-turn. <hi>And having delivered</hi> all <hi>Power into</hi> your <hi>hands, whom</hi> he <hi>and</hi> his <hi>Power</hi> ſought <hi>to</hi> over-turn, he <hi>moved</hi> me <hi>to</hi>
                        <note n="(a)" place="margin">See letter to the Gen. Coun. of Officers, pag. <hi>18.19.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>write to</hi> you <hi>what</hi> yee <hi>ſhould do, and again</hi>
                        <note n="(b)" place="margin">See a ſecond Letter to the ſaid Council, pag. <hi>80, 21, 22</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>warned</hi> you <hi>by</hi> me <hi>a few daies following. And when notwithſtanding</hi> his <hi>warning</hi> yee <hi>had</hi> ſtarted <hi>aſide, and</hi> chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>the</hi> Cauſe <hi>of</hi> Liberty of Conſcience, <hi>the</hi> Dominion of God, <hi>in</hi> your<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                           <hi>May</hi> 12. 1659</note> 
                        <hi>Addreſs to the Parliament,</hi> He <hi>cauſed the</hi>
                        <note n="(d)" place="margin">See Mene Te. <hi>throughout.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>hand-writing</hi> MENE TEKEL <hi>to be drawn againſt</hi> you, <hi>and moved</hi> me <hi>to ſend it</hi> you, <hi>leaving unto</hi> you <hi>therein</hi> yet ſpace and time of Repentance. <hi>And</hi> afterwards, <hi>when</hi> yee <hi>had</hi> Power <hi>again in</hi> your <hi>hands,</hi> He <hi>moved</hi> me<note n="(e)" place="margin">See Let. to the General Coun. of Officers. p. <hi>33. 34.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>to write unto</hi> you, <hi>which</hi> you <hi>not heeding, the</hi> hour of your viſitation paſſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and your Day cloſed into Night. <hi>And now</hi> darkneſs <hi>is over</hi> you, <hi>and the</hi> Word <hi>of the</hi> Lord <hi>which</hi> he <hi>ſpake by</hi> me <hi>to you, through</hi> all, hath taken hold on you, <hi>and</hi> yee <hi>are delivered into the</hi> will <hi>of</hi> your <hi>enemies. And as</hi> yee have profaned the Holineſs of God, which he loved, and married the daughter of a ſtrange God; he hath profaned the Sanctuary of pour ſtrength, and given you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the power of a ſtrange King, <hi>and now</hi> your <hi>ſorrows are mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied, and</hi> your <hi>hope is cut off: and under the</hi> deep <hi>ſenſe of the</hi> burden <hi>of the</hi> Night <hi>which is come upon</hi> you, <hi>the</hi> honeſty <hi>in</hi> you <hi>cries out;</hi> Watchman! What of the Night? Watchman! What of the Night?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To which</hi> I <hi>anſwer in the</hi> Name, <hi>of the</hi> Lord The Morning cometh (<hi>and it is not</hi> long <hi>firſt) wherein the</hi> Lord ſhall riſe up, as in Mount Perazim; and be wrath, as in the Valley of Gibeon; that he may do his work, his Strange work; that he may bring to paſs his Act, his ſtrange Act; <hi>wherein</hi> he will make bare his Arm in the ſight of the Heathen, <hi>and</hi> put on Righteouſneſs as a Breſt-plate, and a Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met of Salvation on his head, and the Garments of Vengeance for clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and Zeal as a Cloake, and according to their deeds, accordingly will he repay fury to his Adverſaries, recompence to his Enemies, and will ſave his afflicted People: <hi>For the</hi> Day of Vengeance is in his heart, and the [Year] of his Redeemed is come; <hi>and the</hi> Son <hi>hath ſaid,</hi> God Almighty is with me, God eternal is my Refuge, who liveth for ever: I live for ever; I ſtand and lift up my Hand to Heaven, and ſay, I live for euer; I come, and my reward is with me; and every eye ſhall ſee me, and the eyes alſo of them who have pierced me; and all
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:29825:22"/> Nations ſhall wall becauſe of me; even ſo Amen. I am ever ye, all ye Powers of Darkneſs; I trample ye under me from mine High Places: I who was dead, and am alive, and behold, I live for evermore, and have the keys of Hell and of Death: I am he who ſhaketh Heaven and Earth; I have overcome, and ſhall inherit all things, and will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due all mine Enemies under me: I will come up on Princes as Morter, and as the Potter treadeth Clay: I will rule them with a Rod of Iron, and break them to pieces as a Potters Veſſel: I will tread the people in mine anger, and trample them in my fury, and their Blood ſhall be ſprinkled upon my Garments, and I will ſtain all my Rayment; for the day of Vengeance is in mine heart, and the <hi>[year]</hi> of my Redeemed is come: O Death! I will be thy Death; O Gravel! I will be thy deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Repentance ſhall be hid from mine eyes. O thou Enemy! Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is come to a perpetual end; and I will reward every man according to his works. Be wiſe therefore, O ye Kings, and be inſtructed ye Judges of the Earth; kiſs the Son leſt he be angry, and ye periſh from the way, when his wrath is kindled but a little. Bleſſed are all they that truſt in him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Therefore</hi> my dear <hi>friends, be not</hi> ye <hi>troubled, neither let</hi> your <hi>hearts faint within</hi> you, <hi>nor be</hi> ye <hi>offended nor ſtumbled becauſe that</hi> your hope is cut off from among men; <hi>becauſe the</hi> proud are counted happy, and they that tempt God are delivered; <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that</hi> Iniquity <hi>ſeems to have the</hi> Day, <hi>and</hi> corrupt Intereſts <hi>the</hi> price <hi>of the</hi> Blood <hi>of</hi> theſe <hi>Nations; becauſe</hi> your body is laid down as the ground, and as the ſtreet to them that go over, who ſay to your ſoul, Bow down, that we may go over: <hi>Becauſe that ſince the time of</hi> theſe <hi>twenty years, wherein ye hoped that God had ariſen to</hi> ſave all the meek of the earth, <hi>and that</hi> he <hi>would not ſlack</hi> his <hi>hand until</hi> he <hi>had</hi> brought forth Judgement into Victory; <hi>the</hi> Day <hi>of</hi> trouble (<hi>as</hi> ye <hi>complain) ſeems to gather</hi> ſo <hi>dark, that none hath been like unto it:</hi> I <hi>ſay, Be not</hi> ye <hi>troubled becauſe of</hi> theſe <hi>things that are</hi> already, <hi>or that</hi> may, <hi>and</hi> ſhall yet <hi>come before</hi> this <hi>night be over; of which the</hi> things <hi>that have been, are but the approaches; for</hi> theſe <hi>things muſt be, that</hi> man <hi>may be ſhewn what he</hi> is, <hi>that</hi> man <hi>may ſee what</hi> he <hi>hath done that</hi> man <hi>may eat of the fruit of</hi> his <hi>doings, and</hi> all <hi>who have leaned upon</hi> him, whoſe breath is in his Noſtrils, and have depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the living God; <hi>that</hi> man <hi>may be ſtript, and brought low, and humbled even to the duſt, and that his</hi> haughtineſs
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:29825:22"/> 
                        <hi>may</hi> be bowed down, and the Lord alone exalted; <hi>that</hi> Iniquity <hi>may have</hi> its Day <hi>wherein to fill up its</hi> meaſure, <hi>and</hi> it is its laſt (<hi>can't</hi> ye <hi>ſuffer it then?) And the</hi> higher it <hi>grows, the</hi> nearer it <hi>is to</hi> its <hi>end; and</hi> its <hi>meaſure muſt be</hi> filled <hi>up, ere deliverance can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, and</hi> refreſhing from the preſence of the Lord; <hi>who is come to do</hi> (himſelf) <hi>what</hi> Man <hi>promiſed, and had</hi> his Day <hi>to do, and ſhould have done, yet did</hi> it <hi>not, but</hi> trifled away time long, <hi>and at length</hi> ſhamefully <hi>quitted and</hi> betrayed it, <hi>and</hi> left the Nation more overgrown with wickedneſs then before, <hi>and</hi> Judgement further off then ever, <hi>and</hi> Equity it cannot enter; <hi>and</hi> he is cutting ſhort the work in Righteouſneſs, <hi>and making</hi> a ſpeedy end in the Earth; <hi>and for</hi> this <hi>purpoſe</hi> is <hi>letting</hi> Iniquity <hi>looſe, that</hi> it <hi>may have</hi> its <hi>ſwing,</hi> its full <hi>career, (the</hi> Hedge <hi>is</hi> up, <hi>the</hi> Fence <hi>is</hi> down, <hi>the</hi> Wall <hi>is</hi> broke; <hi>that</hi> which letted, is taken out of the way) <hi>that</hi> it <hi>may fill up</hi> its <hi>meaſure</hi> quick <hi>and</hi> finiſh <hi>its</hi> courſe, to try a People in whom <hi>He</hi> will be glorified, <hi>that ſo</hi> He <hi>may make of it</hi> an utter end at once; <hi>that</hi> He <hi>may</hi> devour and deſtroy at once; <hi>that</hi> he may conſume the Bryars and the Thorns, Branch and Root, Head and Tail, Soul and Body in one day; <hi>and</hi> place ſalvation in Zion for Iſrael his glory: <hi>And when</hi> Iniquity <hi>ſeems to mount</hi> highest, <hi>then is</hi> its <hi>end</hi> neareſt; <hi>and when</hi> it <hi>ſeems to</hi> careſs it moſt, <hi>then is</hi> its <hi>deſtruction</hi> nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, <hi>even at</hi> the very door. It <hi>muſt be</hi> fully <hi>ripe</hi> ere <hi>the</hi> ſtroke <hi>come that will</hi> ſwinge <hi>it to the</hi> Pit. <hi>It muſt</hi> cry peace and ſafety, ere ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den deſtruction come upon it, as pangs upon a woman in travel, and it ſhall not eſcape. <hi>And let</hi> me <hi>tell</hi> you <hi>for</hi> your <hi>comfort,</hi> its already bundling up, and making ready for the fire. <hi>And though a</hi> Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be determined even upon the whole Earth, and from the Lord of Hoſts I have heard it; yet the Conſumption determined ſhall overflow with Righteouſneſs, and England ſhall be the glory of all Lands, and a Bleſſing to all the Nations-round about her; and from her ſhall go forth Salvation, even to the ends of the Earth; and of her <hi>it ſhall be ſaid after</hi> her <hi>captivity is returned,</hi> Bleſſed be thou O habitation of Juſtice! O Mountain of Holineſs! <hi>The</hi> Eternal God <hi>hath ſpoken</hi> it, <hi>and</hi> the Lord will avenge the Blood of his Elect which cryes day and night unto him; I tell you he will avenge it ſpeedily, yea ſpeedily: But what? even now? The time is come, yea the ſet time is come; the Lord hath ſpoken it. Nevertheleſs when the Son of man cometh, ſhall he find faith in the Earth? But who ſhall live when God doth this? <hi>Is</hi>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:29825:23"/> it <hi>ſaid already, and</hi> it <hi>will ſeem</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Mene Tekel,</hi> pag. 47.</note> impoſſible <hi>as to</hi> man (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> I <hi>have ſaid) But</hi> then it <hi>will be, that the</hi> Lord <hi>may be</hi> known in the earth by the Judgements that he executes. Theſe <hi>things may ſeem</hi> ſtrange (<hi>as</hi> I<note n="*" place="margin">Mene Tekel, pag. <hi>47.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>ſaid) but</hi> the time is at hand; bleſſed is he that endures to the end, the ſame ſhall be ſaved: <hi>And</hi> Judgement muſt begin at the Houſe of God and the time is come; and if it firſt begin at us, what ſhall the end be of them that obey not the Goſpel of God? And if the Righteous ſcarcely be ſaved, where ſhall the wicked and the ungodly appear?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Therefore</hi> I <hi>ſay again to</hi> you, <hi>Be not</hi> ye <hi>troubled, neither faint in</hi> your <hi>minds, nor be offended nor ſtumbled; but</hi> turn in hither, Return—come to the Immortal in you which witneſſeth for God, which gives you the ſence of theſe things, and ſhews unto you all that ye have done, (Is not this the Chriſt?) and reproves you, and ſearcheth your hearts, and tryeth your reins; heed it, believe in it, obey it whileſt ye have time, a little time: This <hi>is</hi> that <hi>which is</hi> come to reign over all for ever; <hi>and</hi> God <hi>is come to ſet it over</hi> all, <hi>even</hi> for ever and ever; <hi>and all</hi> theſe <hi>ſhakings are in order thereunto:</hi> Mans day is done; <hi>but the</hi> Lords day is come: Mans hope <hi>is</hi> cut off, <hi>becauſe</hi> his day <hi>is</hi> done; <hi>but becauſe</hi> his day <hi>is</hi> come, <hi>there is</hi> hope <hi>in the</hi> Lord. I <hi>ſay,</hi> Turn in hither; Return—come to the Immortal (our City of Refuge, <hi>and there is</hi> no <hi>other,</hi> you'l <hi>find it ſo in the end;</hi> I <hi>have ſeen</hi> you <hi>as a</hi> poor deſolate man in the middle of a field, whom I met (in my ſpirit) diſtreſſed in ſpirit, and broken down with ſorrow, not knowing whither to go, or what to do; and the Lord bad me ſay to you, Turn in hither) <hi>that ſo</hi> ye <hi>may finde a</hi> hiding place in the day of the Lords fierce wrath, (<hi>which is</hi> even haſtening on the head of the wicked) <hi>and ſee the</hi> Morning <hi>of the</hi> Eternal Day, which cometh, <hi>yea (as I have ſaid) it is not</hi> long <hi>firſt, yea it hath been ſeen already, and</hi> alſo the Night—<hi>after</hi> it, <hi>which will be</hi> eternal <hi>to</hi> thoſe <hi>that are not gathered into</hi> it. The Night is far ſpent, the day is at hand; if ye will enquire, enquire ye, Return, come; <hi>The</hi> Word <hi>of the</hi> Lord <hi>it is to</hi> you, <hi>and</hi> his <hi>tender Viſitation of Love,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>By his Servant (who hath born</hi> your <hi>burden, and ſuffered that which</hi> ye <hi>are not able to bear</hi>) G. Biſhope.</signed>
                        <dateline>Briſtol, <date>
                              <hi>21. of the</hi> 11th. Month <hi>1659.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:29825:23"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>BUt as for</hi> you <hi>who ſhall not</hi> return <hi>to the</hi> Lord, <hi>nor</hi> come to the immortal in you which witneſſeth for God, <hi>but ſhall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to go on in the</hi> ſtoutneſs <hi>of</hi> your <hi>hearts, and the</hi> ſtubborneſs <hi>of</hi> your <hi>ſpirits, in</hi> Rebellion againſt the Lord; <hi>know</hi> this, <hi>not</hi> onely <hi>what is</hi> already, <hi>but what is</hi> yet <hi>to come to paſs, of that which I have ſpoken to you in the</hi> Name <hi>of the</hi> Lord, <hi>in the</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Mene Tekel.</note> Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing <hi>ſent againſt you,</hi> ſhall aſſuredly come upon you, and ye ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all know that there hath been a Prophet amongſt you; <hi>For,</hi> our God ſhall come, and ſhall not keep ſilence: A fire ſhall devour before him, and it ſhall be very tempeſtuous round about him. He ſhall call to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens from above, and to the Earth, that he may judge his People. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my Saints together to me, thoſe who have made a Covenant with me by Sacrifice. <hi>And</hi> the Heavens ſhall declare his Righteouſneſs, for God is judge himſelf: Selah. <hi>Conſider this ye that forget God, leaſt he tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver. And</hi> the Son of man ſhall come in his glory, and all the holy Angels with him, and ſhall ſit upon the Throne of his Glory; and before him ſhall be gathered all Nations; and he ſhall ſeperate them one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as a Shepherd divideth his ſheep from the goats; and he ſhall ſet the ſheep on his right hand, and the goats on his left; and the King ſhall ſay to them on his right hand, Come ye bleſſed of my Father, receive the Kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world: And unto them on the left hand, Depart from me ye curſed, into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels: And theſe ſhall go away into everlaſting puniſhment, but the righteous into life eternal. <hi>And</hi> ſo I am clear of your blood.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>G. Biſhope.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>I <hi>beheld</hi> till the <hi>Thrones</hi> were caſt down, and the <hi>Ancient</hi> of <hi>Dayes</hi> did fit, whoſe <hi>garment</hi> was <hi>white</hi> as <hi>Snow,</hi> and the <hi>Hairs</hi> of his <hi>Head</hi> like the <hi>Pure</hi> Wool: <hi>His</hi> Throne <hi>was</hi> like the <hi>fiery flame,</hi> and <hi>his</hi> Wheels as <hi>burning fire: A fiery ſtream</hi> iſſued and came forth from before <hi>him; Thouſand Thouſands</hi> miniſtred unto <hi>him,</hi> and <hi>ten thouſand times ten thouſand</hi> ſtood before <hi>him:</hi> the <hi>Judgement</hi> was <hi>ſet,</hi> and the <hi>Books</hi> were <hi>opened;</hi> and <hi>another Book</hi> was opened, which is the <hi>Book of Life;</hi> and the <hi>Dead</hi> were
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:29825:24"/> 
                     <hi>judged</hi> out of <hi>thoſe</hi> things which were <hi>written</hi> in the <hi>Books,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>their</hi> Works. I <hi>beheld</hi> then, becauſe of the <hi>Voice</hi> of the <hi>great</hi> words that the <hi>Horn</hi> ſpake; I beheld even till the <hi>Beaſt</hi> was ſlain, and <hi>his body deſtroyed and given to the burning flame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> And <hi>behold, One</hi> like the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>man</hi> came in the <hi>Clouds</hi> of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and <hi>came</hi> to the <hi>Ancient</hi> of <hi>Dayes,</hi> and <hi>they</hi> brought <hi>him</hi> next before <hi>him,</hi> and there was given <hi>him Dominion</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> and a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> that <hi>all People, Nations,</hi> and <hi>Languages</hi> ſhould ſerve <hi>him; His Dominion is an everlaſting Dominion,</hi> which ſhall not <hi>paſs</hi> away, and <hi>his Kingdom</hi> that which ſhall <hi>not be deſtroyed;</hi> and the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and <hi>Dominion,</hi> and <hi>greatneſs</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> under the <hi>whole</hi> Heaven, ſhall be given to the <hi>People</hi> of the <hi>Saint</hi> of the <hi>Moſt High, whoſe Kingdom</hi> is an <hi>everlaſting Kingdom,</hi> and <hi>all Dominions</hi> ſhall <hi>ſerve</hi> and <hi>obey him. Amen: Hallelujah,</hi> the time is at hand.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>G. B.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
